<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Micro-chronicon, or, A briefe chronology of the time and place of the battels, sieges, conflicts, and other most remarkable passages which have happened betwixt His Majestie and the Parliament from the beginning of these unhappy dissentions to the 25th of March 1647 : together with a catalogue of the Lords, Knights, commanders, and persons of quality slain on either side therein.</title>
            <author>Ryves, Bruno, 1596-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2451</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26225</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09390887</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09390887</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42953</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58043)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42953)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1315:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Micro-chronicon, or, A briefe chronology of the time and place of the battels, sieges, conflicts, and other most remarkable passages which have happened betwixt His Majestie and the Parliament from the beginning of these unhappy dissentions to the 25th of March 1647 : together with a catalogue of the Lords, Knights, commanders, and persons of quality slain on either side therein.</title>
                  <author>Ryves, Bruno, 1596-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[108] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Bruno Ryves--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Chronology.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42953:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MICRO-CHRONICON:</hi> OR, A briefe Chronology of the Time and Place of the Battels, Sieges, Conflicts, and other moſt remarkable Paſſages which have happened betwixt His Majeſtie and the Parliament, from the beginning of theſe unhappy diſſentions to the 25th of <hi>March.</hi> 1647.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together,</hi> With a Catalogue of the LORDS, Knights, Commanders, and perſons of quality ſlain on either ſide therein.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicer.</hi>
               </bibl> Incerti ſunt exitus pugnarum, Marſque eſt communis, qui ſaepe ſpoliantem, jam &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultantem evertit &amp; perculit ab abjecto.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:42953:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42953:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have found in the preceding parts of this <hi>Ruina,</hi> under the Title of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus,</hi> ſome few relations of thoſe many plundring outrages committed on the good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects lives, conſciences, and Eſtates, by the giddy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed Sectaries. In the ſecond place, you have met with their fanaticke fury in deſtroying thoſe once much to be admired <hi>Edifices,</hi> the <hi>Cathedrals</hi> of this Kingdome. In the third, you have ſeen what tyranny they have exerciſed over the learned and pious Divines in and about <hi>London,</hi> And in the fourth place, you have heard the querulous out-cry of that once famous Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> In this laſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part, it reſts only to give you a <hi>Synop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> or ſhort view of the Martiall Actions which did concomitantly occurre in the time of the other, and with it a Liſt of ſuck Noblemen, Knights, Gentlemen and Commanders as peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed on both ſides, in the fury of leſſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n five yeares Warre where the men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cry of ſuch as fell in
<pb facs="tcp:42953:3"/> defence of <hi>Religion, King</hi> and <hi>Lawes,</hi> will deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly live for ever, whileſt the others will dye in their owne putrefaction: In this (as in the former parts) the Reader will eaſily perceive a great deale of candor and impartialitie to goe along even to the end where theſe perſecuting ſubjects met with ſtrange ſucceſſes, not given by God, as a bleſſing upon their bad cauſe, but as a ſcourge for our ſinnes, which when his infinite goodneſſe ſhall deeme to be ſufficiently chaſtiſed, we doubt not but that he will burne thoſe Rods, by deſtroying the <hi>Hydra</hi>-headed multitude of Sects and Hereſies, by re-eſtabliſhing our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sovera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gne in his ancient Rights and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by reducing the Lawes to their old Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, all loyall ſubjects to their Liberties and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and out of the diſſentions and impieties of theſe all-commanding ſubjects make new Rods for their deſerved chaſtiſement, which we ſhall patiently expect in Gods good time.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 25. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:42953:3"/>
            <head>Micro-Chronicon Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſex Mirabilium, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1640" type="year">
               <head>Anno 1640.</head>
               <p>NOvember 3. (after the unhappy breaches of ſome former Parliaments) began that (yet ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) at Weſtminſter, called by His Sacred maieſty, to adviſe with him for the redreſſe of our grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances: But inſtead thereof, (by the prevalencie of a factions party) the Kingdome was voted into unheard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of diſobedience againſt His majeſty, whereby our grievances were multiplyed; Religion and Lawes defaced, by incouragement given to Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, Independants, and all manner of Sectaries, Churches prophaned, the Monuments of the dead vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, the Common prayer Booke throwne away every man being left to the dictate of his private Spirit, and the whole Kingdome engaged in a moſt unnaturall and bloody Warre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1641" type="year">
               <head>Anno 1641.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>May</hi> 12. The Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> after a long and tedious triall, was beheaded on <hi>Tower-hill.</hi> It were hard to tell you by what Law, other then ſome ruſty volumes of conſtructive and arbitrary Treaſon. Howbeit, his life was ſacrificed to
<pb facs="tcp:42953:4"/> appeaſe the thirſt of the multitude. And although His Maieſty (unwillingly) ſigned the Bill; It was no ſmall happineſſe for him and his Poſterity, that His maieſty conceived him not meriting ſo ſevere and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy a puniſhment, as the utmoſt execution of that ſentence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dec.</hi> 15. The Houſe of Commons publiſhed a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of the ſtate of the Kingdome, therein ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth all the Errors of His Majeſties Government (a meere deſigne to alienate the affection of His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from Him) Wherein they alſo declared, that the party of Biſhops and Popiſh Lords in the Houſe of Peeres, had hindred the proceedings of divers good Bils paſſed in the Commons Houſe, concerning the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſundry great abuſes and corruptions both in Church and State. And thereupon the tumultuous and factious people in and about London, reſorted to <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> with clubs and ſwords, crying through the ſtreets, <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and between the two Houſes, <hi>No Biſhops, No Biſhops, No Popiſh Lords,</hi> and abuſing the ſeverall Members of either Houſe, who, they were informed, favoured not their ends: and uſing ſeditious and traiterous ſpeeches againſt His Majeſty him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <div n="January" type="month">
                  <head>January</head>
                  <p>3. His Majeſtie exhibited Articles of High-treaſon againſt the Lord <hi>Kimbolton,</hi> and the five Members, as for other matters, ſo, for endeavouring to ſubvert the fundamentall Lawes and Government of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to deprive. His Majeſtie of his Regall power, and to place an Arbitrary, and Tyrannicall power in ſubjects; and for raiſing and countenancing Tumults, thereby to compell the Parliament to Order, limit, and diſpoſe their proceedings as might concur with their deſignes.</p>
                  <p>4. Upon an Order publiſhed by the Houſe of Com-
<pb facs="tcp:42953:4"/> againſt the <hi>Arreſting of their Members, His Maj. went</hi> in perſon to demand them.</p>
                  <p>5. The Houſes thereupon adjourned themſelves into <hi>London,</hi> and the City took the Members into protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under pretence of <hi>maintaing the priviledge</hi> of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>11. The accuſed five Members were guarded to <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> both by water and land.</p>
                  <p>20. His Majeſty (to compoſe theſe differences) ſent a moſt gracious Meſſage to both Houſes, adviſing them to take into confideration all ſuch particulars as they held neceſſary for upholding his juſt Regall power, and ſetling his Revenue; as alſo for eſtabliſhing Religion, (with due regard to tender conſciences in point of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies) and for ſecuring their Priviledges, and the liberty of the Subject.</p>
                  <p>27. The Houſe of Commons petitioned His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that the Militia, and the Forts and Caſtles might be put in the hands of ſuch men, as <hi>they did conſide in.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>31. Becauſe the major part of Lords would not concurre with the houſe of Commons in the buſineſſe of the Militia, the factious and poore ſort of people in and about London, petition'd the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons (by their owne direction) againſt thoſe Lords, as Malignants, and diſturbers of their Peace, and threatned to remove them, ſo they withdrew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and the Militia was carried by the remaining party of the Lords.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="February" type="month">
                  <head>February</head>
                  <p>2. The Lords and Commons petitioned His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, that he would forthwith put the Tower of London, and all other Forts, and the whole Militia of the Kingdome, into the hands of ſuch perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as <hi>they ſhould recommend unto him,</hi> to which His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty returned this moſt Gracious Anſwer, that when he ſhould know, the extent of Power which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb facs="tcp:42953:5"/> to be eſtabliſhed in thoſe Perſons, whom they deſired to be the Commanders of the Militia, in the ſeverall Counties; and likewiſe to what time it ſhould be limited, that no Power ſhould be executed by His Majeſty alone without the advice of Parliament; then he would be content to put in all the places both of Forts and Militia, ſuch perſons as both Houſes of Parliament, ſhould either approve, or recommend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, ſo that they declared before unto His Majeſty the names of ſuch perſons: unleſſe ſuch perſons ſhould be named, againſt whom he ſhould have juſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable exceptions. In the interim,</p>
                  <p>11. His Majeſtie (to ſhew his reall intention to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the (needleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e) feares of his people) was content to accept of S. <hi>John Conyers,</hi> in the place of S. <hi>John Byron</hi> to be Lievtenant of the Tower.</p>
                  <p>23. The Queenes Majeſtie tooke ſhipping at <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> having been driven before from <hi>White-hall</hi> by the frequent tumults of the factious and rude people; and ſoone after His Majſty went to <hi>New-market,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Yorke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>24. The Houſes of Parliament ſent a meſſage unto His Majeſty, wherein they deſired that the Prince might not be removed from <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> leaſt it might be a cauſe to promote jealouſies and feares, &amp;c. To which His Majeſty returned, that he knew not what anſwer to give, not being able to imagine from what grounds they proceeded. But if any information had beene given to that purpoſe; His Majeſty much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the ſame might be examined to the bottome, and then he hoped, that their feares and jealouſies would be afterwards continued only with reference to His Majeſties Rights and Honour.</p>
                  <p>24. The Lords and Commons voted 2500000. Acres of Land in <hi>Ireland</hi> to be aſſigned, allotted, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded amongſt ſuch as ſhould diſburſe any ſummes of
<pb facs="tcp:42953:5"/> money, for reduceing of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame day His Majeſty (being glad to receive any Propoſition that might repaire the calamity of his diſtreſſed Kingdome of <hi>Ireland;</hi>) not only aſſented unto their Propoſitions; but alſo offered to venture his owne Royall Perſon for the recovery of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to contribute any other Aſſiſtance he could to that ſervice, by parting with any profit, or advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his owne there—And yet they were not aſhamed afterwards to ſuſpect, nay, accuſe His Majeſtie of Granting Commiſſions for raiſing the Rebellion there.</p>
                  <p>25. The Houſes preſented an Ordnance to His Majeſty for ſettleing of the Militia according as <hi>they had thought fit;</hi> to which they deſired His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties aſſent.</p>
                  <p>28. His Majeſty (for many weighty reaſons) retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Negative anſwer; wherein (amongſt other rationall expreſſions) this was one: That he could not conſent to deveſt himſelfe of the juſt power which God and the Lawes of this Kingdome had placed in him, for the defence of his people, and to put it into the hands of others for any indefinite time, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>March</head>
                  <p>1. The Houſes Petition'd His Majeſty (then at <hi>Theobalds</hi>) concerning the Militia, wherein they threatned him; that if His Majeſty ſhould perſiſt in his denyall, and not aſſure them by their Meſſengers of his Royall aſſent to their former deſires, they ſhould be enforced to diſpoſe of the Militia, by their owne Authority, in ſuch manner as had beene formerly propounded to him; and that they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to doe it accordingly, with many other unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expreſſions.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day His Majeſty retuned them anſwer; That for the Militia he had thought ſo much of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:42953:6"/> anſwer before he ſent it, and was ſo much aſſured that the ſame was agreeable to what in Juſtice, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they could aske, or he in honour grant, that he ſhould not alter it in any point, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>2. The Houſes voted that the Kingdome ſhould be put into a poſture of defence by their owne Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in ſuch a way as they had already agreed upon.</p>
                  <p>15. His Majeſty (upon his removeall from <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington</hi> to <hi>Yorke</hi>) ſent a moſt gracious Meſſage to both Houſes, wherein he earneſtly deſired that they would uſe all poſſible induſtry in expediting the buſineſſe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> intimating withall, that no inconvenience ſhould happen to that ſervice by his abſence, and that if the misfortunes and Calamities of his poore Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Subjects there ſhould grow upon them (though His Majeſty ſhould be deeply concerned in, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their ſufferings) he ſhould waſh his hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the world, from the leaſt imputation of ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in that neceſſary and pious worke; with many other moſt gracious expreſſions for the begetting of a good underſtanding betweene him and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the due obſervation of the Lawes of the Kingdome concerning the Militia, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>16. His Majeſtie ſet forth a moſt gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation for putting the Lawes againſt Popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants in due execution.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1642" type="year">
               <head>Anno 1642.</head>
               <p>28. A Paper was ſent from the two Houſes, unto His maj. concerning the Earle of <hi>Warwick</hi> to be made Admirall of the Seas, notwithſtanding that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had already appointed Sir <hi>John Pennington</hi> upon the Recommendation of the Admirall, againſt whom no fault was or could be alleadged.</p>
               <p>31. His Majeſty ſignified his reſolution upon that point, which was that he would not alter him, whom
<pb facs="tcp:42953:6"/> he had already appointed to command this yeares fleete.</p>
               <div n="April" type="month">
                  <head>Aprill</head>
                  <p>8. His Majeſty ſent a moſt gracious Meſſage to the Parliament, concerning his firme reſolution of going in Perſon to <hi>Ireland,</hi> for ſuppreſſing the Rebells there, and thereby ſo to ſettle the peace of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the ſecurity of this, that the very name of feares and Jealouſies might have beene no more heard of.</p>
                  <p>9. The Lords and Commons declared that they intended a due and neceſſary reo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Lyturgie of the Church, and to take away nothing in one, or the other, but what was evill, and juſtly offenſive, or at leaſt unneceſſary and burthenſome.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day they Petitioned His Majeſty to give leave to remove the Magazine from <hi>Hull,</hi> to the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of London, and for executing of ſixe condemned Prieſts, which His Majeſty (in his wonted mercy) had Reprieved, becauſe he had beene certainly informed that they were (by ſome reſtraint) diſabled to take the benefit of His Majeſties Proclamation.</p>
                  <p>18. The Houſes Petitioned His Majeſty to deſiſt from his intended paſſage to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and from all preparation of men and armes tending thereunto, and to leave the managing of that Warre to themſelves. Whereunto the King returned a moſt gracious anſwer, and was contented to ſtay ſometime to ſee the event of things, and not purſue his reſolution, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>22. The Gentry of <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> Petitioned His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty that the Magazine at <hi>Hull</hi> might not be removed thence.</p>
                  <p>23. Hereupon His Majeſty went in Perſon to view his Armes, and Munition there, where being come, he ſound the Gates all ſhut upon him, and the Bridges
<pb facs="tcp:42953:7"/> drawn up by the command of that Arch-Traitor Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> who then commanded a Garriſon there, and from the Walls flatly denyed His Majeſty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance; nor would he ſuffer the Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and his Nephew the Prince <hi>Elector,</hi> (who had gone thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the day before) to be let out to His majeſty, till after ſome Conſultation.</p>
                  <p>28. It was voted that Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> had herein done nothing but in obedience to the command of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="May" type="month">
                  <head>May</head>
                  <p>12. The Militia being taken from His Majeſty (againſt the Law, and His Majeſties conſent) and put in execution; And his Magazine at <hi>Hull</hi> (being his owne proper goods) taken from (and imployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt) him; and Sir <hi>John Hothams</hi> Treaſon coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, and defended by the two Houſes; His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty reſolved to have a Guard (the Parliament ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had one for three moneths before, upon imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry jealouſies) only to ſecure his Perſon; to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at His Majeſties owne Charge: In which he (this day) deſired the concurrence and aſſiſtance of the Gentry of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> who willingly thereunto agreed, as conceiving themſelves bound to doe the ſame by their Allegiance.</p>
                  <p>20. It was voted by both Houſes, that the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eavy War againſt the Parliament: which they did on purpoſe to excuſe themſelves for raiſing a Rebellion againſt His majeſty, as appeared within few dayes after.</p>
                  <p>27. His majeſty by his Proclamation forbad all his ſubjects belonging to the Traind-bands, or mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia of the Kingdome, to riſe, martch, muſter, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, without his conſent, or warrant, upon paine of puniſhment according to the Lawes.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day His majeſty commanded the Gentry
<pb facs="tcp:42953:7"/> and others of the County of <hi>Yorke,</hi> to meete upon <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> moore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="June" type="month">
                  <head>June</head>
                  <p>18. His maieſty by his Proclamation, forbad all leavies of forces, without his conſent.</p>
                  <p>20. His maieſty by another Proclamation, declared the lawfullneſſe and uſe of the Commiſſions of Array, and commanded obedience to be given to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners therein named, in the Execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                  <p>30. His maieſty ſent out his Warrant, for ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning of all Gentlemen, and others, being Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, who were charged with horſes for His maieſties ſervice, or had liſted themſelves to attend perſonally for his ſecurity to make their appearance at <hi>Yorke, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 7. following.</p>
                  <p>2. They offered to His maieſty 19. Propoſitions, which ſtruck at Regall power it ſelfe; and would trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it to, and ſettle it in the Houſes of Parliament for ever: And ſo of Monarchy would have made this an Ariſtocracy and Democracy (ſuitable to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they intended in the Church, the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie:) and upon the Kings refuſall of them,</p>
                  <p>10. They publiſhed Propoſitions for bringing in of money, &amp;c. to raiſe an Army.</p>
                  <p>11. The Lords Ordered, that all Armes, Ammunition, Powder, Light-horſes, &amp;c. that were, or ſhould be convayed towards the North, ſhould be ſtayed.</p>
                  <p>12. Letters, feigned here at home, yet, given out to be ſent from <hi>Amſterdame,</hi> intimating preparation of Ordnance, Piſtols, and Ammunition there, to be transported to His maieſty of purpoſe to deterre the ſimple people, and to poſſeſſe them with a beleefe that His maieſty intended to make Warre with the Parliament;) were read in the Houſe of Commons, and Ordered to be Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:8"/>
                  <p>16. His maieſty diſavow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d any preparations, or intentions in him to leavie Warre againſt his Houſes of Parliament. And the Lords and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hers of his Privie Councell there teſtified in Juſtification of His maieſty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="July" type="month">
                  <head>July</head>
                  <p>2. His maieſties Ship called the providence landed in the Cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k of <hi>Kenningham</hi> neare <hi>Hull;</hi> till which time His m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſty had not a Barrell of Powder, nor any Armes, or Ammunition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hatſoever.</p>
                  <p>12. The pretended two Houſes (Rebelliouſly) voted, that the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> ſhould be Generall of their Army, and that they would live and dye with him.</p>
                  <p>30. They Ordered 100000. l. of the monyes which was come in upon the ſubſcriptions for <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be imployed to the diſturbance of the peace of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in bloody Warre againſt His Sacred maieſty, the miſchievous, illegall, and uniuſt diverſion of which monies (contrary to the expreſſe words of the Act of Parliament concerning the ſame) was the only cauſe of the Rebells ſucceſſe, and of the waſting of His maieſties Armies there, for want of timely ſupplies and payment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="August" type="month">
                  <head>Auguſt</head>
                  <p>1. The Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> cauſed all the men then raiſed (being in number about 10000) to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to officers, and divided into regiments, which men had beene raiſing ever ſince the 12. of <hi>July</hi> 1642. at which time he was made Generall of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells.</p>
                  <p>6. The Earle of <hi>Bedford</hi> having fruitleſſely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged the Lord marqueſſe of <hi>Hertford</hi> in <hi>Sherburne Caſtle</hi> for foure daye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> before, retreated to <hi>Yevell;</hi> whereof 9. Commanders, tooke divers Priſoners, and routed the reſt; ſo as he marched away, and after
<pb facs="tcp:42953:8"/> divided his ſmall forces, going himſelfe into <hi>Wales</hi> and Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> (now deſervedly Lord) <hi>Hopton</hi> into <hi>Cornwall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>8. The Lords and Commons by their Declaration gave full power and Authority to the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and all the reſt of their Commanders to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight with, kill, and ſlay, all, or any that ſhould oppoſe the militia.</p>
                  <p>9. The Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and all his adherents were Proclaimed Traitors: And His maieſty made his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious offer of pardon to him and ſuch of his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as ſhould within ſix dayes lay downe their Armes.</p>
                  <p>10. His maieſty declared (by his Proclamation) that no Popiſh Recuſant ſhould ſerve him in his Army.</p>
                  <p>18. The Rebells at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> declared all men Traitors that ſhould aſſiſt His maieſty with Horſe, Armes, and money, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>22. His maieſty (then at <hi>Notingham</hi>) ſent unto them a moſt gracious meſſage, for a Treaty: But they refuſed it.</p>
                  <p>25. His maieſty ſet up his Standard Royall at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> for raiſing of Forces to ſuppreſſe the Rebells then marching againſt him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="September" type="month">
                  <head>September</head>
                  <p>19. His maieſty made his ſpeech and proteſtation in the head of his Army betweene <hi>Stafford</hi> and <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>23. Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> with about 11. Troopes of horſe gave a great overthrow to the Rebells in <hi>Wikefield</hi> neare <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame day they Ordered, that all the Regiments of foot, and Troupes of horſe in <hi>London,</hi> and all parts of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould within 48. houres march to the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> to be imployed againſt His ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="October" type="month">
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:9"/>
                  <head>October.</head>
                  <p>4. His maieſty by his Proclamation adiourned part of <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme; but the Houſes would take no notice thereof.</p>
                  <p>23. Was that ſignall great Battaile fought between <hi>Keinton</hi> and <hi>Edge-hill</hi> by His maieſties Army, and that of the Parl. led by the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> wherein the Parl. loſt above 70. Colours of Cornets and Enſignes, and His maieſty but only 16. Enſignes, and not one Cornet. The exact number that were ſlaine on bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h ſides in this Battaile is not knowne: But it is moſt certaine that the Parl. loſt above three for one. His maieſty himſelfe was in the Bataile, whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courage put life in every man, his ſacred Perſon being expoſed to ſo much danger as all good men doe tremble to remember. His Royall Sonnes (the two young Princes) <hi>Charles</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> being alſo in the field in very much danger, if God (whoſe cauſe it was) had not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their heads in the day of Battaile.</p>
                  <p>24. His maieſty offered a generall pardon to all ſuch as ſhould lay down Armes, and returne to their obedience.</p>
                  <p>27. His maieſty to compleat his victory in <hi>Keinton</hi> field, drew his whole Army before Banbury; but after the fireing of one ſmall Drake, the Parl. forces there ſubmitted to His mai. mercy (which were in number about 800. foot (of the Earle of <hi>Pete boroughs,</hi> and Lord <hi>Says</hi> Regiments) with ten Colours, and a troupe of horſe) and yeelded the Towne and Caſtle to the King: at which time the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> with his ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered forces, were crept over the river <hi>Avon</hi> into <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> (full 8. miles backward from the place where they were beaten) there to ſecure thoſe few he had left under the protection of the ſtrong ſcituate Towne and Caſtle, leaving behind him above 20. Waggons loaden
<pb facs="tcp:42953:9"/> with Powder and other Ammunition.</p>
                  <p>His maieſty offered a pardon to the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="November" type="month">
                  <head>November</head>
                  <p>12. His majeſty, after foure houres fight, forced the Town of <hi>Brainceford,</hi> where Lievtenant Col. <hi>Quarles</hi> that commanded in chiefe was ſlaine, and at leaſt 400. more of the Parliaments killed and drowned, and many taken Priſoners, amongſt whom was that Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand of ſedition, <hi>Iohn Lilburne, Defendour of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. The next morning (being Sunday) certaine of the Parl. forces had come down the Thames from <hi>Kingſton</hi> with 18. peeces of Ordnance, which (ſo ſoone as they could diſcerne (for it was a very miſty morning) they fired againſt <hi>Sion</hi> houſe, and His majeſties Traine of Artillery, but did little or no harme: Whereupon His maieſty commanded ſome Peeces to be drawne downe into the meadow, and to the river ſide over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and likewiſe a Demicanon to be planted neare the South end of the Towne. All which were ſo iudiciouſly plyed, that they ſhot through their Boats and Barges, and at laſt fired the powder in one of them, which blew up many of them: The reſt tooke them to their heeles, leaving behind them their mangled boats and barges, with all their Ordnance and the remainder of their Ammunition; on which His maieſty preſently ſeized, and afterwards (the yeare being ſpent) made an Honorable and ſafe retreat to the Citie of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. His maieſties Forces (under the command of Lievtenant Generall <hi>Wilmot</hi>) ſtormed, and tooke the Towne of <hi>Marlborough</hi> defended by one <hi>Ramſey</hi> (a Scot) and about 500. foot: <hi>Ramſey</hi> and diverſe of the prime Reſiſtants brought Priſoners to <hi>Oxford,</hi> all their Armes taken and foure Colours.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:10"/>
                  <p>The ſame day, the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> laid ſiege to <hi>Tadcaſter,</hi> and by ſeverall aſſaults on the Towne (from tenne of the Clock in the forenoone, till ſeven at night) killed Captaine <hi>Lyſter,</hi> and 60. more of the Parl. who found ſuch hot ſervice that they ſtole away in the night to <hi>Cawood</hi> and <hi>Selby,</hi> leaving <hi>Tad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter</hi> fortified for His maieſties ſervice.</p>
                  <p>19. A great victory was obtained by the Lord <hi>Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> neare <hi>Bodmin</hi> in the County of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> 900 of the Parl. ſlaine and taken Priſoners, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>22. The Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> aſſaulted and tooke the Town of <hi>Saltaſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>27. The Forces (Commanded by <hi>John Hampden</hi>) aſſaulted <hi>Brill</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire</hi> (then a Garriſon for His maieſty) but were ſhamefully repulſed by His maieſties forces there, under the command of Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerard</hi> the then Governour thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="February" type="month">
                  <head>February</head>
                  <p>1. Lievtenant Generall <hi>King</hi> and Lievtenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Goring</hi> defeated 400. foot and three Troupes of the Parl. horſe neare unto <hi>Yarum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Cirenceſter,</hi> or <hi>Ciceſter,</hi> in <hi>Glouceſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhire</hi> was taken by his highneſſe Prince <hi>Rupert.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. The Queenes maieſty left the <hi>Hague</hi> and went to <hi>Sciveling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>16. Her maieſty reimbarked in the Princeſſe Royall of Great <hi>Brittaine;</hi> And,</p>
                  <p>Her maieſty came within ſight of <hi>Flamborough</hi> head.</p>
                  <p>20. She caſt Anchor in the harbour of <hi>Burlington</hi>-Bay.</p>
                  <p>22. Her maieſty landed at <hi>Burlington</hi> Key.</p>
                  <p>24. This morning, foure Ships and a Pinnace in the Parl. ſervice, which came over-night into the roade, made above 100 great ſhot at the houſes in the Key, for two houres ſhooting croſſe-barre-ſhot, and bullets of 12. pound weight, all of them aimed ſo neere as they
<pb facs="tcp:42953:10"/> could, at the place where the Queene lay: inſomuch that Her maieſty was forced to make what haſte She could out of her bed, and to get her ſelfe under the ſhelter of an hill to ſave her life from the fury of thoſe bloudy rebels. But God preſerved Her maieſty both by ſea and land.</p>
                  <p>In this moneth, Sir <hi>Richard Lawdy,</hi> with the Forces from <hi>Hereford,</hi> routed a great body of the Parl from <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> at <hi>Cover,</hi> on the borders of that County; where that valiant and faithfull Gentleman was ſlaine out of a window.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>March</head>
                  <p>18, 19. was a great battaile on <hi>Hopton-heath</hi> in Stafford-ſhire, wherein <hi>Gell</hi> and <hi>Brereton,</hi> two coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebels, were totally routed by His maieſties forces under the command of the right honourable <hi>Spencer,</hi> then Earle of Northampton, who was there unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately ſlaine, with Col: <hi>Middleton,</hi> and ſome few others on His maieſties part.</p>
                  <p>23. <hi>Grantham</hi> taken by Col: <hi>Charles Cavendiſh</hi> for His maieſty, and afterwards the Works demoliſhed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1643" type="year">
               <head>Anno 1643.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aprill</hi> 3. His highneſſe Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> aſſaulted, entered, and poſſeſſed himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of that ſeditious towne of <hi>Burmingham.</hi> Here he noble Earle of <hi>Denbigh</hi> received a wound, where of he afterwards dyed.</p>
               <p>11. A body of the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l forces under young <hi>Hotham</hi> their then Generall, totally routed, the Generall put to flight, the moſt of his men ſlaine and taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. This was performed by Colonell <hi>Caven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh,</hi> neare unto <hi>Ancaſter</hi> in the County of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>21. The Cloſe at <hi>Lichfield</hi> after three Weekes fiege, was yeelded up to his highneſſe Prince <hi>Rupert.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:11"/> This place was defended by a part of thoſe forces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of the late Lord <hi>Brooke,</hi> a great lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in this rebellion, and a moſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litious enemy to the Church, who was killed in his aſſaulting this Church by a ſhot into the eye, on Saint <hi>Chads</hi> day, who was the firſt Biſhop of this See, in memory of whom this Cathedrall was built, and called S. <hi>Chads</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>30 His Excellency the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtles</hi> forces encountered with and totally routed above 3000 of the Parl. forces which were going to releeve the Town of <hi>Leeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. <hi>James</hi> Earle of <hi>Northampton,</hi> the true heire of his Fathers loyaltie and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lour encountered with a body of the Parl. forces in <hi>Midleton-Cheny</hi> towne-field neare to <hi>Banbury,</hi> conſiſting of about 700. foot, and five Troups of Horſe, where he totally routed their foot, killed 217. upon the plaine, tooke above 300. Priſoners, and all their Ordnance and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>16. The Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> aſſaulted a great body of the Parliament then intrenched neare <hi>Stratton</hi> on the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> fought with them full 10. houres, and having ſpent his Ammunition, inſomuch that he had not powder left to ſerve one houre longer, fell upon them with Swords, piques, and muſquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocks: and, with unexpreſſible valour, wholly routed their Army, killed many hundreds of them in the place, wounded many more, tooke 1700. priſoners, whereof above 30. Commanders, all their Canon, money, (being three thouſand pounds) Armes and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>30. The Queenes maieſty was moſt Traiterouſly voted a Traitor, for her love ſo exemplarily expreſſed to the King her husband.</p>
               <p>30. <hi>M. Robert Yeomans,</hi> and <hi>M. George Bourcher.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:11"/> two Citizens of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> were there publiquely mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by that Cowardly Colonell <hi>Nathaniel Fines,</hi> for their Loyaltie to His Majeſty.</p>
               <div n="June" type="month">
                  <head>June</head>
                  <p>18. His Highneſſe Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> beate up the Quarters of the Parl. forces at <hi>Poſtcombe &amp; Chinner</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> obtained a great victory in <hi>Chalgrove</hi>-field, and utterly defeated the Parl. horſe-men and Dragoons, ſlew divers of their Commanders, amongſt whom was Colonell <hi>John Hampden</hi> (one of the five Members accuſed (by His Majeſtie) of High Treaſon) who in this fight received his mortall wound, in this very <hi>Chalgrove</hi> field, where he firſt muſtred, and drew up men in Armes to put in execution the ungodly Ordnance for the Militia.</p>
                  <p>31. His Excellency (the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle)</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a great victory againſt the Northerne Forces under the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> upon <hi>Adderton</hi> Heath within the County of <hi>Yorke.</hi> In which fight His Excellency ſoone put the Parl. to flight; their Generall <hi>Fairfax</hi> being forced to ſhift (with one poore Toupe of horſe) into <hi>Leeds,</hi> leaving the reſt to the mercy of the victor.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="July" type="month">
                  <head>July</head>
                  <p>1. Sir <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> with three Troups out of his owne Regiment, routed 400. of the Parl. horſe and Dragoones commanded by Colonell <hi>Middleton,</hi> neare <hi>Padbury</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire,</hi> ſlew about 100. of them, took 40. priſoners, and thereby prevented a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of the Parliament</p>
                  <p>Col. (now Lord) <hi>Jermin,</hi> with thoſe forces that guarded her Maj. out of the North (aſſiſted by Col. <hi>Haſtings</hi> (now Lord <hi>Loughborough</hi>) took <hi>Burton</hi> upon <hi>Trent</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame day the Marqueſſe of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> beſieged <hi>Bradford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Bradford</hi> taken, and in it 2000. priſoners, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:42953:12"/> their Horſe, Armes, and Ammunition.</p>
                  <p>Hereupon the Parl. deſerted the towne of <hi>Halli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax,</hi> and preſently after Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmeley</hi> fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Beverley,</hi> and took it for His Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>5. M. <hi>Tompkins</hi> and M. <hi>Challenor</hi> were moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly murthered in <hi>London,</hi> for their fidelity to His Majeſty. And the ſame 5. day was a fight on <hi>Lands<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>downe Hall,</hi> betwixt His Majeſties Forces, under the Command of the noble Marqueſſe of <hi>Hartford,</hi> and the Parliaments Army under Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> who (after 11. houres fight) ſtuck their lighted matches in the hedges, and ran away. Their Foot were abſolurely routed, and all diſperſed: their loſſe of Officers &amp; Horſe very great, many hundreds of their men were killed; His Majeſties Forces having the pillage of the field. And here was that valiant Knight Sir <hi>Bevill Greenvill</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately ſlaine in the front of his men.</p>
                  <p>13. About 4. aclock in the afternoone, the King and Queenes Majeſty met at <hi>Edge-hill,</hi> where the Parl. (<hi>October</hi> 23. 1642.) had received ſo great an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow: and the ſame day and houre His Majeſties Forces (under the Command of the Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Generall of the horſe, the Earle of <hi>Carnarvon,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Byron</hi>) obtained another great &amp; ſtrange victory upon <hi>Round-way Downe,</hi> with 1500. Horſe, and two ſmall peeces of Cannon only: wherewith they totally routed the Parl. Army under the command of that old beaten Souldier Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> conſiſting of above 2500. foot, and 2000. horſe, beſides five hundred Dragooners, took eight peeces of braſſe Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſlew 600. of them in the place, tooke above nine hundred priſoners, all their Cannon, Armes, Ammunition, Waggons, Baggage, and Victuall, 28. foot-Enſignes, nine Cornets, and left not one of them, but what was either killed, taken priſoner, or narrowly eſcaped.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:12"/>
                  <p>24. His Highneſſe Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> having joyned his Forces to his brothers and the whole body of their ſtrentgh being brought together, they ſate down before <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> and began their Batteries.</p>
                  <p>26. They gained the Out works.</p>
                  <p>27. The Citie and Caſtle were delivered to His Maj. withall the Ordnance, Armes and Ammunition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="August" type="month">
                  <head>Auguſt</head>
                  <p>3. <hi>Corfe-Caſtle</hi> (in the Iſle of <hi>Purbecke</hi>) was fallen upon by the Parl. forces, who were ſhamefully repulſed by the Gallantry of Captaine <hi>Laurence:</hi> Above 60. were killed in the place, the reſt hearing of the Earle of <hi>Carnarvons</hi> approach, ran away.</p>
                  <p>5. <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> ſummoned, and ſurrendred unto the E. of <hi>Carnarvon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>9. About this, the Caſtle and Iſle of <hi>Portland</hi> were reduced under His Maj. Command: And the Towne and Haven of <hi>Weymouth</hi> and <hi>Melcombe</hi> ſubmitted to His Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>20. Col. <hi>John Digby</hi> defeated the Forces of <hi>Bidde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and <hi>Barnſtaple.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="September" type="month">
                  <head>September</head>
                  <p>2, 3. The Townes of <hi>Biddeford, Appleford</hi> and <hi>Barnſtaple</hi> delivered up their ſeverall Garriſons to His Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>The ſame third day His Highneſſe Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> aſſaulted <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4. His Highneſſe gained the great Sconce, and immediately after the Towne and Caſtle, which were delivered unto His Highneſſe, with all the Ordnance, Armes, and Ammunition.</p>
                  <p>The Parl. Army (ſtealing out of <hi>Glouceſterſhire</hi> towards <hi>London</hi>) ſurpriſed part of a new raiſed Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of His Majeſties Horſe at <hi>Cyrenceſter,</hi> but being overtaken by Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> with His Majeſties Horſe neare <hi>Auburne</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> many great bodies of their
<pb facs="tcp:42953:13"/> foot were routed, and many of them ſlaine in the place. Here was the Marqueſſe <hi>De la Vieuville</hi> taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who was afterwards murthered in cold bloud; becauſe they underſtood he was ſomething allyed to the Queenes Majeſty. Hereby the Parl. Army was greatly retarded, inſomuch that His Majeſty had time to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them with his foot, and</p>
                  <p>20. upon an hill neare <hi>Newbury</hi> and <hi>Enborne</hi> heath, His Maieſty fought with them, who were ſeated in the moſt advantagious place imaginable; yet in deſpight of all their Cannon, Foot and Horſe, His Majeſtie beat them from their ground; gained the hill and one Peece of their Ordnance, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly routed all their Horſe upon the heath. The moſt that were killed in this fight of His Majeſties forces, exceeded not the Number of three hundred; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſix hundred of the Parl. loſt their lives there, and a great number of them were wounded.</p>
                  <p>In this fight were ſlaine the moſt Noble and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Earle of <hi>Carnarvon,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Sunderland,</hi> the Lord <hi>Viſcount Faulkland,</hi> Colonell <hi>Morgan</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>William Simpcots,</hi> with ſome other Gentry and Commanders. After this the Parl. forces were further purſued and routed againe, ſo as they fled into <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> where they durſt not ſtay, but left the Town for His majeſty.</p>
                  <p>25. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> pernitious Confederacy, called the natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Covenant, was taken by the Members of the Houſe of Commons at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in Saint <hi>Margarets Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1644" type="year">
               <head>Anno 1644.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 18. The Prince of <hi>Harcourt</hi> Lord Ambaſſadour extraordinary from the <hi>French</hi> King and Queene Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent (after he had beene moſt barbarouſly uſed by the Parl.) came ſafe to <hi>Oxford,</hi> where he had entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:42953:13"/> more ſuitable to the worth of ſo great a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage.</p>
               <p>His Majeſties under the Command of the Lord <hi>Widdrington,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Henderſon</hi> (a Scot) recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a defeat neare <hi>Horne</hi>-Caſtle in <hi>Lincolneſhire,</hi> by the Parl. forces under the Command of <hi>Mancheſter, Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> and <hi>Fairfax,</hi> there were taken priſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs neare 600. of His Majeſties forces, Sir <hi>Ingram Hopton</hi> and ſome few others ſlaine, not without ſome conſiderable loſſe to the Parliament.</p>
               <div n="November" type="month">
                  <head>November</head>
                  <p>11. An Ordnance for authorizing the Counterfeit Great Seale.</p>
                  <p>21. Sir <hi>William Armine,</hi> and others (ſent by the Parl. at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) arrived at <hi>Edenborough</hi> with Articles of accord, and advance money, to haſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the Scots invaſion.</p>
                  <p>27. The Kings Meſſenger hanged at London, for diſcharging his Duty, in ſerving His Majeſties Writ.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="December" type="month">
                  <head>December</head>
                  <p>4. <hi>Hawarden</hi> Caſtle ſurrendred to His Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>8. <hi>John Pym</hi> died (<hi>De morbo pediculoſo</hi>) at <hi>Derby houſe</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>12. <hi>Beeſton</hi> Caſtle aſſaulted and taken for His Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>21. <hi>Lapley</hi> houſe taken by Capt. <hi>Heaveningham</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>28. Col. <hi>Nathaniell Fiennes,</hi> one of the firſt that appeared in this unnaturall Warre, was in a Court of War at S. <hi>Albans,</hi> by his owne fellows, ſentenced to be hanged for a Coward.</p>
                  <p>29. The ſtately Screen of Copper richly gilt, ſet up by <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh in his Chappell at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> was by Order of both Houſes reformed, that is, broken downe and ſold to Tinkers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1645" type="year">
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:14"/>
               <head>Anno 1644.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 16. The perfidious Scots (contrary to the ſolemne Pacification) invaded this Kingdome.</p>
               <p>22. The members of Parl. aſſembled a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Oxford</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to His mai. Proclamation.</p>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>March</head>
                  <p>2. The Scots came over the river of <hi>Tyne,</hi> and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>King</hi> purſueing them in the rere, forced them into <hi>Sunderland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. <hi>Hopton</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Shropſhire</hi> taken by Colonell <hi>VVoodhouſe</hi> for His majeſty.</p>
                  <p>18. <hi>VVardour</hi> Caſtle in <hi>VViltſhire</hi> (after long ſiege) was taken by Sir <hi>Francis Dodington</hi> for His maieſty.</p>
                  <p>22. <hi>Newarke,</hi> after three weekes ſiege releived by His Highneſſe Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> where all the Parl. Forces were totally defeated; and ſoone after <hi>Lincolne, Sleeford,</hi> and <hi>Gainsborough</hi> were quitted by the Parliament.</p>
                  <p>23. <hi>Sturton</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> ſurrendred to S. <hi>Gilbert Gerard</hi> then Governour of <hi>VVorceſter</hi> for His maieſty.</p>
                  <p>24. <hi>Apeley Houſe</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire</hi> taken by Col. <hi>Ellis,</hi> for His maieſty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="April" type="month">
                  <head>Aprill</head>
                  <p>3. 6. <hi>Longford Houſe</hi> and <hi>Tongue</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Shropſhire</hi> ſurrendred to His highneſſe Prince <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. <hi>Glouceſter</hi> Forces aſſaulted <hi>Newent,</hi> but were gallantly repulſed and purſued by Col. <hi>Minne</hi> the Governour thereof, and forced to leave two peeces of their Cannon behind them, and many dead bodies before the works.</p>
                  <p>17. The <hi>Queenes</hi> maieſty began her iourney from <hi>Oxford</hi> into the <hi>VVeſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:14"/>
                  <p>The ſame day <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ampton B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yan</hi> in <hi>Herefordſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> (a Caſtle of S. <hi>Robert Harleys</hi>) was ſummoned, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred (at mercy only) to S. <hi>Michael VVoodhouſe,</hi> for His maieſty.</p>
                  <p>The ſame 17. day was <hi>Dunfreize</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> taken in by the Marqueſſe of <hi>Mountroſſe</hi> for his maieſty.</p>
                  <p>22. <hi>Stutcombe</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhire</hi> aſſaulted and taken by his highneſſe Prince <hi>Maurice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="May" type="month">
                  <head>May</head>
                  <p>6. The Garriſon of <hi>Lathom Houſe</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> made (amongſt divers others) a moſt remarkable ſally, wherein they killed many of the Beſiegers in their Trenches, purſued the reſt and killed neare 300. of the Parl. in the purſuite, and took three peeces of their Ordnance.</p>
                  <p>12. The forces from <hi>Plymouth</hi> aſſaulted <hi>Mount-Egcombe Houſe</hi> in <hi>Cornewall,</hi> and repulſed.</p>
                  <p>24. The Parl. having formed two Armies, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting for the moſt part of the <hi>London</hi> Trained Bands and Auxiliaries under the Command of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler</hi>) this day ioyned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Blewbury</hi> in <hi>Berkſhire</hi> and bent their courſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Abbingdon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>25. Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> aſſaulted and took <hi>Stopford</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire.</hi> Hereupon <hi>Latham Houſe</hi> (after 18. weekes ſiege) was timely releived.</p>
                  <p>28. His highneſſe Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> ſummoned, ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and took <hi>Bolton</hi> (the <hi>Geneva</hi> of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> (as the Brethren uſe to call it) the firſt town in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and conſequently in <hi>England,</hi> that put in execution the Militia, as the readieſt meanes to ruine the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
                  <p>29. The Parl. Armies ſevered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> marching from <hi>Abbingdon</hi> to <hi>Iſlip,</hi> with purpoſe to diſtreſſe <hi>Oxford</hi> on the North part, as <hi>VValler</hi> at
<pb facs="tcp:42953:15"/> 
                     <hi>Abingdon</hi> on the South part.</p>
                  <p>30. The Parl. forces attempted to paſſe, to croſſe the River <hi>Charwell</hi> at <hi>Goſworth-bridge;</hi> but were gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repulſed.</p>
                  <p>31. <hi>Waller</hi> attemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d to paſſe <hi>Iſis</hi> at <hi>Newbridge,</hi> but being alſo repulſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e retired to <hi>Abingdon,</hi> where (to revenge himſelfe) he demoliſhed <hi>Abingdon</hi> Croſſe, defaced the Church, burnt all the Tables and Cheſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boards, and plundred moſt of the people of their Goods.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="June" type="month">
                  <head>June</head>
                  <p>1. They againe attempted in ſeverall places at once, to croſſe the river <hi>Charwell,</hi> but ſped as little, being ſtill beaten off with great loſſe, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly at <hi>Goſworth</hi> Bridge, where they loſt above-100. men.</p>
                  <p>3. His Majeſty perceiving the Parl. intention to beſiege <hi>Oxford,</hi> left a ſufficient ſtrength for defence thereof, and to disburthen the Citie of unneceſſary ſorce) marched with the reſt of His Army (this eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evening) towards <hi>worceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4. The Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> perceiving the Kings forces drawne away, paſſed <hi>Charwell</hi> with his Army, and hearing of His Majeſties departure from <hi>Oxford,</hi> haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after.</p>
                  <p>5. The Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> went this day as farre as <hi>Chipping Norton</hi> after the King.</p>
                  <p>6. But unwilling to looſe his labour any longer, returned to <hi>Burford,</hi> where he deputed Sir <hi>VViliam VValler</hi> to proceed in the adventure of King catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that himſelfe might have the honour of taking in <hi>Leſtithiell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>11. <hi>Dudly</hi> Caſtle releeved by His Majeſties forces from <hi>VVorceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>12. Col. <hi>Gage,</hi> with ſome forces from <hi>Oxford</hi> took in <hi>Borſtall</hi> houſe.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:15"/>
                  <p>16. The Lady <hi>Henrietta</hi> borne at <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>18 His Majeſty in <hi>worceſterſhire</hi> (having intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that the Parliament Armie were now ſevered, (whilſt Sir <hi>william waller</hi> to get before the King r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n into <hi>Staffordſhire</hi>) reſolved to reinforce himſelfe with the Regiments left at <hi>Oxford,</hi> &amp; encount<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Sir <hi>william,</hi> to which end His Majeſty returned, and came this day to <hi>VVitney.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>20. Col. <hi>Shuttleworth</hi> with 400. Men attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to beat up a part of Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> Quarters at <hi>Blackburne</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire:</hi> But S. <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> was ſo ready for him, that he killed and tooke above 100. of his men, and made himſelfe and the reſt ſhift for their lives.</p>
                  <p>22. Sir <hi>VVill. VValler</hi> having run himſelfe out of breath, gave over the purſuite of the King (the rather for that then His Maj. was provided for him) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon His Majeſty directed his march towards the Pari. aſſociated Counties, and came this night to <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> where he received the joyfull news of His Queenes ſafe delivery of the Princeſſe <hi>Henrietta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>25. S. <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> totally routed 300 Horſe and 100. Dragoons under the command of Col. <hi>Shuttle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> at <hi>Colne,</hi> on the borders of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> had exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution on them for three miles, wounded Col. <hi>Shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleworth</hi> himſelfe, who with ſome few eſcaped, the reſt were either killed, or taken, and the Colours and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners brought to Prince <hi>Rupert.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>26. <hi>VValler</hi> to recruite his weary Army from the Garriſons of <hi>Gloceſter, VVarwick, Coventry, Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Kenelmworth</hi> Caſtle, had this day a Rendezvouz in <hi>Keinton</hi> field, whereof the King having no ice, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his martch towards him, and quartered this night at <hi>Brackley.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>28. This day His Majeſty comming before <hi>Banbury,</hi> ſound <hi>VValler</hi> drawne up in Battalia Weſtward
<pb facs="tcp:42953:16"/> from the Towne, on the ſide of <hi>Crouch hill,</hi> taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the hills, bogs, and ditches.</p>
                  <p>29. His Maieſty diſcerning that <hi>Waller</hi> would not come into the plaine, nor could be aſſaulted as he lay, but with much diſadvantage, removed ſomewhat North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to ſee if thereby he could draw him from his Station, which accordingly was done, for <hi>Waller</hi> likewiſe advanced on the other ſide the river, whereupon the Kingat <hi>Cropready</hi> marched further off the river, leaving the bridge, in hope to draw them over, which <hi>Waller</hi> greedily apprehending as an advantage, put over 2000. horſe and a great body of foote, with 14. peeces of Cannon. <hi>VVallers</hi> Army being thus divided were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately charged by the Kings reare, the Earle of <hi>Cleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> horſe, and Sir <hi>Bernard Aſtleys</hi> foot, routing all that had paſt the bridge, whilſt the E. of <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> charged the reſt of their horſe, that were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding over. In this fight were ſlaine above 300. Parl. and many of them taken priſoners, with their 14. peeces: There were ſlaine on His Majeſties port two Gallant Knights, Sir <hi>William Butler,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke,</hi> and not above 14. common Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. And ſo much for <hi>Wallers</hi> Army this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="July" type="month">
                  <head>July.</head>
                  <p>In the begining of this moneth His Highneſſe Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> marched out of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> with a conſiderable Army for the reliefe of <hi>Yorke,</hi> which had beene two moneths beſieged by an aggregate body of the Parl. conſiſting of the Earle of <hi>Manceſters</hi> Army, the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> and the rebellious Scots under the Command of <hi>Leſley.</hi> The Prince had no ſooner releeved <hi>Yorke,</hi> but drew forth after the Parl Army, &amp; on <hi>Marſton moore</hi> there began a terrible fight, wherein His highneſſe at firſt had much the better, tooke their Ordnance, and many of them Priſoners, inſomuch that <hi>Leſley</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:42953:16"/> the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> thinking all had beene loſt, fled many miles from the place where the Battell was fought, and never came to the remainder of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, till two daies after the fight, but in concluſion (whether by fate that attends the event of Warre, or by neglect, I know not) the fortune of the day turned, and the Parl forces recovered their loſt Ordnance, and tooke ſome of the Princes Baggage, and with it Sir <hi>Charles Lucas,</hi> Colonell <hi>Porter,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Tiliard</hi> Priſoners. In this Battaile were ſlaine on His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties part, the Lord <hi>Cary,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Metham,</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Ewer,</hi> Colonell <hi>Towneley,</hi> with ſome others of note, and about 1500. common ſouldiers. On the Parl. part were ſlaine Sir <hi>Charles Fairfax</hi> with many other of their Commanders, and at leaſt 3000 common Soldiers.</p>
                  <p>This done, the Parl. rally and ſit downe againe before <hi>Yorke,</hi> which was ſurrendred within three weeks after upon honourable conditions, which were moſt perfidiouſly broken by the Parl. forces.</p>
                  <p>6. The Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> routed 350. of the Parl. neare <hi>Warmiſter,</hi> which were purſued above 20. miles by Sir <hi>Francis Dodinglon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>15. His Maj came to <hi>Bath</hi> with his Army; which day the Queenes Maj. arrived ſafe at <hi>Breſt</hi> in <hi>Brittany,</hi> notwithſtanding 50 great ſhot made at her by <hi>Batty</hi> the Parl. vice-Admirall.</p>
                  <p>23. The King made a ſpeech to the <hi>Sommerſetſhire</hi>-men on <hi>King's-moore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>31. <hi>Middleton</hi> (a Scot) furiouſly aſſaulted <hi>Denning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Caſtle, and received a moſt ſhamefull repulſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="August" type="month">
                  <head>Auguſt</head>
                  <p>1. His Maieſty with his Army paſſed into <hi>Cornewall</hi> over <hi>Tamar</hi> at <hi>Polton</hi> bridge in purſuite of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> whom he had now chaſed through <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:17"/>
                  <p>25. His Maj. gained from the Parl. the Caſtle of <hi>Leſtithiel,</hi> where their Army lay ſtrongly encamped.</p>
                  <p>30. The Parl. Horſe in the night paſſed between His Majeſties Quarters, and fled towards <hi>Plymouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>31. The Parl. foote making towards <hi>Foy,</hi> were beaten from five Peeces of their Ordnance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="September" type="month">
                  <head>Semptember</head>
                  <p>2. The Parl. Army being deſerted by their Generall the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> (who with the Lord <hi>Roberts</hi> fled to <hi>Plymouth</hi> in a Cock-boate the night paſt) this day yeelded up to His Majeſty all their Traine of Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>viz,</hi> 49. peeces of faire braſſe Ordnance, above 200. Barrells of Gun-powder, with match, Bullet, &amp;c. proportionable, above ſeven hundred Carriages, and betwixt eight and nine thouſand Armes: His Majeſty out of his wonted clemency granting them their lives.</p>
                  <p>5. His Majeſty having obtained ſo compleat a victory over the Parl. Forces, did (formerly after the defeat of <hi>Waller</hi>) from <hi>Taveſtocke</hi> ſend his ſecond meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of peace to <hi>VVeſtminſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>About this time the Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> and major Generall <hi>Mackdonald</hi> obtained a great victory over the Parl. Forces upon <hi>Newbigging Moore</hi> in <hi>Scotland:</hi> and took S. <hi>Johns</hi> Towne.</p>
                  <p>And within 14. dayes after this victory they obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a ſecond victory over another body of the Parl. forces in that Kingdome neare unto <hi>Aberdene;</hi> and ſoone after the Marqueſſe took the Town of <hi>Aberdene</hi> and all the Ordnance, &amp;c. and therein many of their fugitives.</p>
                  <p>11. The Garriſon of <hi>Baſing</hi> (after 18. Weekes ſiege) was releeved from <hi>Oxford</hi> by Sir <hi>Henry Gage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>12. <hi>Ilfercombe</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> rendred to Generall <hi>Goring</hi> for His Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>17. <hi>Barnſtable</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> (that had formerly
<pb facs="tcp:42953:17"/> revolted upon the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his approach) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to His Majeſty and obtained from him their ſecond pardon.</p>
                  <p>23. Colonell <hi>John Fines</hi> (having beſieged the Caſtle of <hi>Banbury</hi> above a moneth before) hired his men to ſtorme it in five places, in all which they were ſhamefully beaten oft with great loſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1646" type="year">
               <head>Anno 1644.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>October</hi> 7. In the night Sir <hi>Richard Greenvil</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained the Towne of <hi>Saltaſh</hi> by ſtorming.</p>
               <p>25. The E. of <hi>Northampton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Gage</hi> raiſed the ſiege of <hi>Banbury</hi>-Caſtle, fell upon Col. <hi>Iohn Fines</hi> his flying Troupes, ſlew and took many of his men and horſe, one peece of Ordnance, all their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and many Armes.</p>
               <p>27. The Parliament having thus loſt two of their Armies, called the third (under the Earle of <hi>Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> Command, out of the aſſociated Counties) and forced other Regiments out of <hi>London</hi> to ſight His Maj. who was now advanced to <hi>Newbury</hi> with part of his Army, where the Parliament apprehending a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, in regard that the reſt of His Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>forces were not come up, fell upon His Maieſties Quarters, but were beaten off, with the ſlaughter of above 1000. of their men.</p>
               <div n="November" type="month">
                  <head>November</head>
                  <p>6. His maieſty had his Rendezvouz on <hi>Bullington greene,</hi> betwixt <hi>VVallingford</hi> and <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>9. <hi>Dennington</hi> Caſtle releeved, the Parliament not daring to withſtand His maieſties Army.</p>
                  <p>17. His maj. advanced towards the Parl. forces to <hi>Hungerford,</hi> upon whoſe approach the Army left the field. Whereupon His mai. ſent S. <hi>Henry Gage</hi> with a party to releeve the wants of <hi>Baſing,</hi> but the Parl. had raiſed their ſiege before his approach.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:18"/>
                  <p>19. <hi>Monmouth</hi> that had lately beene betrayed by <hi>Kirle,</hi> was bravely regained by the Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Ragland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>23. His Majeſty having thus victorouſly defeated two of their Armies, and driven away the third, came to <hi>Oxford</hi> to entertaine an Overture of Peace (certaine Propoſitions being the ſame day come thither from <hi>London</hi>) having diſpoſed of his Army to their Winter Quarters.</p>
                  <p>26. A Vote paſſed by the Members of the Houſe of Commons at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> for the utter aboliſhing and taking away of the book of Common Prayer, with intention to ſet up a new device, to be called a Direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory inſtead thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="December" type="month">
                  <head>December</head>
                  <p>13. <hi>His</hi> Majeſty (out of <hi>His</hi> wonted deſire of Peace) ſent the Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton</hi> to the Houſes of Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for a Treaty, as the beſt expedient for Peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Helmſeley</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> (after 16. weekes ſiege) was delivered up to the Parl. upon honourable Conditions.</p>
                  <p>22. Col. <hi>Eyre</hi> with ſome horſe from <hi>Newarke</hi> took two Troups of horſe at <hi>Upton</hi> belonging to the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> brought the men, Colours, Horſes and Armes all ſafe to <hi>Newa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>23. Sir <hi>Alex. Carew</hi> was beheaded on <hi>Tower-hill</hi> by Martiall Law, for intending to deliver up the Iſland at <hi>Plymouth</hi> to His Majeſty. This man was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be moſt violent againſt His Majeſty in the beginning of this Warre; but having ſome diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to become a Convert, his fellow members thought fit to diſpatch him to another world.</p>
                  <p>24 S. <hi>William Vaughan</hi> fell on a party of the Parl. neare <hi>Welch Poole</hi> Commanded by S. <hi>John Price,</hi> killed ſome, wounded others, took divers Priſoners, and many Horſes and Armes.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:18"/>
                  <p>28. Maſter <hi>Blakes</hi> houſe at <hi>Pinnell</hi> neare <hi>Calne</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> taken by a party of the Lord <hi>Gorings</hi> forces.</p>
                  <p>31. The Members at <hi>VVeſtminſter</hi> voted Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> to be their new Generall, caſhiering the E. of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> with whom (<hi>July</hi> 12. 1642) they had ſworn to live and die.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="January" type="month">
                  <head>January</head>
                  <p>1. Young <hi>Hotham</hi> was beheaded on <hi>Tower-hill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> his father was likewiſe behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by Martiall Law. Here the Reader may take notice of a ſpeciall marke of Gods judgement, for (<hi>Apr.</hi> 23. 1642.) when old <hi>Hotham</hi> denyed His Maj. admittance into <hi>Hull,</hi> he held up his hands, and prayed God <hi>never to proſper him or his poſterity, if he were not His Majeſties loyall Subject:</hi> And now ſee both father and ſonne adjudged by their fellow-members, and condemned by their owne beloved Martiall Law, for intending to deliver up <hi>Hull</hi> to His Majeſty.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day the Lord <hi>Aſtley</hi> took <hi>Lypyate</hi> houſe in <hi>Glouceſterſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale</hi> totally routed Col. <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes</hi> Regiment of horſe at <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>10. The Lord <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Canturbury</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed on <hi>Tower-hill.</hi> It would be too long here (where we aime at Brevitie) to ſet downe the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of his Impriſoment, the prepoſterous procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt him in his Triall, and his pious magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity at the time of his Death, his Sermon on the Scaffold (whereof here followeth a true Copie) will ſatisfie the world, that he dyed innocently, and (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich is more) that His Majeſtie hath beene moſt unjuſtly accuſed of any inclination to Popery.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:42953:19"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="sermon">
                              <opener>
                                 <salute>Good People.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>THis is an uncomfortable time to preach, yet I ſhall begin with a text of Scripture. <hi>Heb. 12. 2. Let us run with patience that race which is ſet before us, Loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king unto Jeſus the author and finiſher of our Faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſſe, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet downe at the right hand of the Throne of God.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>I have been long in my <hi>Race,</hi> and how I have loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to <hi>Jeſus the author and finiſher of my Faith,</hi> Hee beſt knowes: I am now come to the end of my <hi>Race,</hi> and here I find the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> a death of <hi>ſhame;</hi> but the <hi>ſhame</hi> muſt be <hi>deſpiſed,</hi> or no comming to the <hi>right hand of God; Jeſus deſpiſed the ſhame</hi> for me, and God forbid but I ſhould <hi>despiſe the ſhame</hi> for Him; I am going a pace (<hi>as you ſee</hi>) towards the Red Sea, and my feet are now upon the very brinke of it; an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I hope, that God is bringing me to the <hi>Land of promiſe,</hi> for that was <hi>the way through which he led his People:</hi> But before they came to it, Hee inſtituted a <hi>Paſſeover</hi> for them, a <hi>Lamb</hi> it was, but it muſt be <hi>eaten with ſowre Hearbs,</hi> I ſhall obey, and labour to digeſt the <hi>ſow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>e Hearbs,</hi> as well as the <hi>Lamb.</hi> And I ſhall remember it is <hi>the Lords Paſſeover;</hi> I ſhall not thinke of the <hi>Hearbs,</hi> nor be angry with the hand which ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth them; but looke up only to him who inſtituted that, and gov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>rnes theſe; For men can have <hi>no more power over men, then what is given them from above.</hi> I am not in love with this paſſage, through the Red Sea, for I have the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>akneſſe and infirmities of fleſh and blood pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ntifully in me, And I have prayed with my Saviour, <hi>ut tranſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>et Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>x iſte,</hi> that <hi>this Cup</hi> of red wine <hi>might paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap> from me:</hi> But if not, <hi>Gods will (not mine) be done;</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> I ſhall moſt willingly <hi>drinke of this Cup</hi> as deep as he pleaſes, and enter this Sea, yea and paſſe through it, <hi>in the way that he ſhall lead me.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <pb facs="tcp:42953:19"/>
                              <p>But I would have it remembred (Good people) that when Gods Servants were in this boyſterous Sea, and <hi>Aaron</hi> among them, the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> which perſecuted them (and did in a manner drive them into the Sea) were drowned in the ſame waters, while they were in purſuit of them; I know <hi>my God whom I ſerve,</hi> is as able to deliver me from this Sea of Blood, as he was to deliver the <hi>three Children</hi> from the Furnace, and (I moſt humbly thank my Saviour for it) my Reſolution is now, as theirs was then; They <hi>would not worſhip the image the King had ſet up,</hi> nor will I the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations which the people are ſetting up; nor will I forſake the <hi>Temple and the truth of God,</hi> to follow the bleating of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Calfe in <hi>Dan</hi> and in <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thell.</hi> And as <hi>for this people,</hi> they are at this day mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably miſſed, (God of his mercy open their Eyes that they may ſee the right way) for at this day <hi>the blind lead the blind,</hi> and if they goe on, <hi>both will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall into the ditch.</hi> For my ſelfe, I am (and acknowledge it in all humility) a moſt grievous ſinner many wayes, by thought, word and deed, and I cannot doubt, but that God hath mercy in ſtore for me (a poore penitent) as well as for other ſinners, I have now upon this ſad occaſion, ranſacked every corner of my heart, and yet (I thanke God) I have not found (among the many) any one ſin which deſerves death by any knowne Law of this Kingdome; And yet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I charge nothing upon my Judges; for if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon proofe (by valuable witneſſes) I or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther innocent, may be juſtly condemned; And (I thank God) though the weight of the ſentence lie hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy upon me, I am as quiet within, as ever I wa in my life. And though I am not only the firſt Arch-Biſhop, but the firſt man that ever dyed by an <hi>Ordinance of Parliament,</hi> yet ſome of my Predeceſſours have gone this way, though not by this meanes; For <hi>Elphegus</hi>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:42953:20"/> was hurried away and loſt his head by the <hi>Danes;</hi> and <hi>Symon Sudbury</hi> in the fury of <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes; Before theſe, Saint <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> had his head danced off by a lewd woman; and Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſubmitted his head to a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſword. Many Examples (great and good) and they teach me patience; for I hope my Cauſe in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will looke of another dye, then the colour that is put upon it here. And ſome comfort it is to me, not only that I goe the way of theſe great men in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall generations, but alſo that my Charge (as ſoule as tis made) looks like that of the <hi>Jewes</hi> againſt Saint <hi>Paul, (Acts</hi> 25. 3.) For he was accuſed for the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Temple, i. e. Religion;</hi> And like that of Saint <hi>Steven (Acts</hi> 6. 14.) for breaking the <hi>Ordinances which Moſes gave, i. e.</hi> Law and Religion, <hi>the holy place and the Temple (verſe</hi> 13.) But you will ſay, doe I then compare my ſelfe with the integrity of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Steven?</hi> No, farre be that from me; I onely raiſe a comfort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to my ſelfe, that theſe great Saints and ſervants of God were laid at in their times, as I am now. And it is memorable, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> who helped on this Accuſation againſt Saint <hi>Steven,</hi> did after fall under the very ſame himſelfe. Yea, but here is a great clamour that I would have brought in Popery; I ſhall anſwer that more fully by and by; In the meane time you know what the Phariſees ſaid againſt Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>If we let him alone, all men will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him,</hi> Et venient Romani, <hi>and the Romans will come, &amp; take away both our place and the Nation.</hi> Here was a cauſeleſſe Cry againſt Chriſt that <hi>the Romans will come;</hi> And ſee how juſt the judgement of God was; they crucified Chriſt for feare leſt the <hi>Romans</hi> ſhould come, and his death was it which brought in the <hi>Romans</hi> upon them, God puniſhing them with that which they moſt feared: And I pray God this clamour
<pb facs="tcp:42953:20"/> of <hi>Venient Romani</hi> (of which I have given no cauſe) help not to bring them in; for the Pope never had ſuch a Harveſt in <hi>England</hi> ſince the Reformation, as he hath now upon the Sects and Diviſions that are amongſt us. In the mean time, <hi>by Honour and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by good report and evill report, as a deceiver and yet true,</hi> am I paſſing through this world, 2 Cor. 6. 8. Some particulars alſo I think it not amiſſe to ſpeake of.</p>
                              <p>And firſt, this I ſhall be bold to ſpeak of the King our gracious Soveraigne; He hath beene much tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced alſo for bringing in of Popery; but on my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (of which I ſhall give God a very preſent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt) I know Him to be as free from this charge, as any man living; and I hold Him to be as ſound a Proteſtant (according to the Religion by Law eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as any man in this Kingdome; And that he will venture His Life as farre, and as freely for it; and I think I doe, or ſhould know, 60th his affection to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and His grounds for it, as fully as any man in <hi>England.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>The ſecond particular is concerning this great and Populous City, (which God bleſſe) Here hath beene of late, a faſhion taken up, to gather hands, and then goe to the Great Court of this Kingdome, (the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and clamour for Juſtice, as if that great and wiſe Court, before whom the Cauſes come, (which are unknowne to the many) could not, or would not doe Juſtice, but at their appointment. A way, which may endanger many an <hi>Innocent</hi> man, and pluck his blood upon their owne heads, and perhaps upon the Cities alſo: And this hath beene lately practiſed againſt my ſelfe; The Magiſtrates ſtanding ſtill, and ſuffering them openly to proceed from pariſh to pariſh without check; God forgive the ſetters of this (with all my heart I beg it) but many well meaning people are
<pb facs="tcp:42953:21"/> caught by it. In Saint <hi>Stevens</hi> caſe, when nothing elſe could ſerve, <hi>they ſtirred up the people againſt him;</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> went the ſame way, when he had killed Saint <hi>James,</hi> yet he would not venture upon Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> till he found how the other <hi>pleaſed the people.</hi> But take heed of having your <hi>hands full of blood,</hi> for there is a time (beſt knowne to himſelfe) when God (above other ſinnes) <hi>makes Inquiſition for bloud,</hi> and when that Inquiſition is on foot, the Pſalmiſt tells us, <hi>That God remembers</hi> (but that is not all) <hi>He remembers and forgets not the complaint of the poore,</hi> that is, whoſe blood is ſhed by oppreſſion, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. take heed of this. <hi>It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God,</hi> but then eſpecially, <hi>when he is making Inquiſition for blood;</hi> And (with my prayers to avert it) I doe heartily deſire this City to remember the Prophefie that is expreſſed, <hi>Jer. 26. 14, 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As for me, behold I am in your hand: doe with me as ſeemeth good and meet unto you. But know yee for certaine, that if yee put me to death, ye ſhall ſurely bring inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood upon your ſelves, and upon this City, and the Inhabitants thereof, &amp;c.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>The third particular is the poor Church of <hi>England.</hi> It hath flouriſhed and beene a ſhelter to other neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Churches, when ſtormes have driven upon them. But, alas, now it is in a ſtorme it ſelfe, and God onely knowes whether, or how it ſhall get out; and, which is worſe then a ſtorme from without, it is become like an Oak cleft to ſhivers with wedges made out of its owne body, and at every cleft prophaneſſe and irreligion is entring in, while as <hi>Proſper</hi> ſpeakes (in his ſecond Booke <hi>De vitae contemptu cap. 4.) Men that introduce prophaneſſe are cloaked over with the name</hi> Religionis Imaginariae, <hi>of Imaginary Religion;</hi> for we have loſt the Subſtance and dwell too much in Opinion, and that Church which all the Jeſuites ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations
<pb facs="tcp:42953:21"/> could not ruine, is fallen into danger by her owne.</p>
                              <p>The laſt particular (for I am not willing to be too long) is my ſelfe: I was borne and baptized in the boſome of the Church of <hi>England</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law; in that profeſſion I have ever ſince lived, and in that I come now to dye; This is no time to diſſemble with God, leaſt of all in matter of Religion; and therefore I deſire it may be remembred, I have alwayes lived in the Proteſtant Religion, eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> and in that I now come to dye. What clamour and ſlanders I have endured for labouring to keepe an Uniformity in the externall ſervice of God, according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline of this Church, all men know, and I have abundantly felt.</p>
                              <p>Now at laſt I am accuſed of <hi>High Treaſon</hi> in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: a crime which my ſoule ever abhorred; this Treaſon was charged to conſiſt of theſe two parts, <hi>An endeavour to ſubvert the Lawes of the Land,</hi> and a like <hi>Endeavour to overthrow the true Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion eſtabliſhed by Law.</hi> Beſides my Anſwers to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Charges, I proteſted my innocency in both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>It was ſaid, Priſoners proteſtations at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ar muſt not be taken.</hi> I can bring no witneſſe of my heart <hi>&amp;</hi> the intentions thereof; therefore I muſt come to my Proteſtation, not at the Bar, but my Proteſtation at this houre and inſtant of my death; in which I hope all men will be ſuch charitable Chriſtians, as not to think I would dye and diſſemble, being inſtantly to give God an accompt for the truth of it: I doe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here in the preſence of <hi>God,</hi> and his holy Angells, take it upon my death, That I never endeavoured the ſubverſion either of <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Religion;</hi> and I deſire you all to remember this Proteſt of mine concerning mine innocency, in theſe, and from all Treaſons whatſoever. I have beene accuſed likewiſe as an enemy to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:
<pb facs="tcp:42953:22"/> No, I underſtand them and the benefit that comes by them too well to be ſo; But I did miſlike the miſgovernments of ſome Parl. many wayes, and I had good reaſon for it, for <hi>Corruptio optimieſt peſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>a,</hi> there is no corruption in the world ſo bad, as that which is of the beſt thing in it ſelfe: For the better the thing is in nature, the worſe it is corrupted. And that being the higheſt Court, over which no other hath ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, when tis miſ-informed or miſ-governed, the Subject is left without all remedy. But I have done, I forgive all the world, all and every of thoſe bitter Enemies which have perſecuted me, and humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be forgiven of God firſt, and then of every man, whether I have off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>nded him or not, if he doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that I have. Lord doe thou forgive me, and I beg forgiveneſſe of him, And ſo I heartily deſire you to joyn in Prayer with me.</p>
                              <p>OEternall God and mercifull Father, looke downe upon me in mercy, in the riches and fulneſſe of all thy mercies looke upon me; but not till thou haſt nailed my ſinnes to the Croſſe of Chriſt, not till thou haſt bathed me in the blood of Chriſt, not till I have hid my ſelfe in the wounds of Chriſt: that ſo the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due unto my ſinnes may paſſe over me. And ſince thou art pleaſed to try me to the uttermoſt, I humbly beſeech thee give me now in this great inſtant, full pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, proportionable comfort, and a heart ready to dye for thy honour, the King's happineſſe, and this Churches preſervation. And my zeale to theſe, farre from Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy be it ſpoken, is all the ſinne, humane frailties except<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>d, and all incidents thereto, which is yet known to me in particular, for which I now come to ſuffer; I ſay in this particular of Treaſon; but otherwiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my ſins are many and great: Lord pardon them all, &amp; thoſe eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, what ever they are, which have drawne downe this preſent judgement upon me: and when thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:42953:22"/> given me ſtrength to beare it, doe with me as ſeemes beſt in thine own eyes: &amp; carry me through death that I may looke upon it in what viſage ſoever it ſhall appeare to me, <hi>Amen.</hi> And that there may be a ſtop of this iſſue of bloud, in this more then miſerable Kingdome, (<hi>I ſhall deſire that I may pray for the people too, as well as for my ſelfe</hi>) O Lord, I beſeech thee, give grace of repentance to all bloud-thirſty people; but if they will not repent, O Lord confound all their devices, defeat and fruſtrate all their deſignes and endeavours upon them, which are or ſhall be contrary to the Glory of thy great Name, the truth and ſincerity of Religion, the eſtabliſhment of the King and his poſterity after him in their juſt rights and Priviledges, the honour and conſervation of Parliaments in their juſt power, the preſervation of this poore Church in her truth, peace, and patrimony, and the ſettlement of this diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and diſtreſſed People under their ancient Lawes, and in their native Liberties. And when thou haſt done all this in meere mercy for them, O Lord fill their hearts with thankfullneſſe, and with religious dutifull obedience to thee and thy Commandements all their dayes: So <hi>Amen,</hi> Lord Jeſus <hi>Amen,</hi> and receive my Soule into thy Boſome <hi>Amen. Our Father which art in heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>11. Sir <hi>Henry Cage</hi> Governour of <hi>Oxford</hi> intended to have raiſed a fort at <hi>Cullom-Bridge,</hi> but the deſigne being treacherouſly diſcovered, he was prevented, and in the attempt moſt unfortunately received a ſhot, whereof, within two houres after, he dyed. His Body was afterwards interred at <hi>Oxford</hi> with funebrious exequies, and ſolemnities anſwerable to his merits, who having done His Majeſty ſpeciall ſervice, was, whilſt living, generally beloved, and dead is ſtill uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall lamented: He was a moſt valiant and expert
<pb facs="tcp:42953:23"/> Souldier; and a moſt pious and learned Gentleman, as may appeare by that learned tract of his, written and printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> entituled the prerogative of man, or his Soules immortalitie, and high perfection defended, &amp;c. His daily refreſhed memory makes me treſpaſſe on the Readers Patience with this</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="elegy">
                              <head>ELEGIE Vpon the never-enough lamented death of <hi>Sir HEN: GAGE, the moſt deſired Governour of</hi> Oxford.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>SO <hi>Titus</hi> called was, <hi>The worlds delight,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>And ſtraight-way dyed; The envious Siſters ſpight</l>
                                 <l>Still the great favourite: The darling head</l>
                                 <l>Unto the Fates is alwayes forfeited.</l>
                                 <l>Our Life's a Chaſe, where (though the whole Herd fly)</l>
                                 <l>The goodlieſt Deere is ſingled out to dye.</l>
                                 <l>And as in beaſts, the fatteſt ever bleeds,</l>
                                 <l>So amongſt men, he that doth braveſt deeds.</l>
                                 <l>He might have liv'd, had but a cowards feare</l>
                                 <l>Kept him ſecurely ſculking in the reare:</l>
                                 <l>Or like ſome ſucking Colonell, whoſe edge</l>
                                 <l>Durſt not advance a foot from a thick hedge:</l>
                                 <l>Or like the wary <hi>Skippon,</hi> had ſo ſure</l>
                                 <l>A ſuite of Armes, he might (beſieg'd) endure:</l>
                                 <l>Or like the Politick Lords, of a different skill,</l>
                                 <l>Who thought a Saw-pit ſafer, or a hill;</l>
                                 <l>Whoſe valour in two organs too did lye</l>
                                 <l>Diſtinct; the one in's eare, th'other in his eye.</l>
                                 <l>Puppets of War! Thy name ſhall be divine,</l>
                                 <l>And happily augment the number Nine,</l>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:42953:23"/>
                                 <l>But that the Heroes, and the Muſes ſtrive</l>
                                 <l>To owne thee dead, who wert them all alive.</l>
                                 <l>Such an exact compoſure was in thee,</l>
                                 <l>Neither exceeded <hi>Mars,</hi> nor <hi>Mercurie.</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>Twas juſt, though hard, thou ſhouldſt dye Governour</l>
                                 <l>Oſth' Kings cheife Fort of Learning, and of War.</l>
                                 <l>Thy death was truly for thy Garriſon,</l>
                                 <l>Thou dy'dſt projecting her Redemption.</l>
                                 <l>What unto <hi>Baſing</hi> twice (ſucceſſefull ſpirit)</l>
                                 <l>Was done th'haſt effected here in merit.</l>
                                 <l>The Bridge was broken downe: <hi>The Fort alone</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>GAGE was himſelfe, the firſt and the laſt ſtone.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Goe burne thy Faggots <hi>Browne;</hi> and grieve thy Rage</l>
                                 <l>Lets thee out-live the gentle graſp of <hi>GAGE.</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>And when thou read'ſt in thy <hi>Britanicus</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>The boaſted ſtory of his death, ſay thus:</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>The Valour I have ſhowne in this, was Crime,</l>
                                 <l>And <hi>GAGES</hi> Death will brand me to all Time.</l>
                              </lg>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>In this Moneth the <hi>John</hi> of <hi>London</hi> belonging to the Eaſt <hi>India</hi> Merchants, was brought to <hi>Briſtoll</hi> (by the Loyalty of Captaine <hi>Mucknell</hi> and the reſt of the Officers and Mariners of the Ship) for his Majeſties Service, wherein were 26. Peeces of Ordnance moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, 17000. l. in money beſides ſome other good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities. For which good ſervice the ſaid Captaine <hi>Mucknell</hi> had the honour to be the firſt Knight that ever the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> made.</p>
                  <p>And within a few daies after another Ship called the <hi>Fame</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> was by tempeſt forced into <hi>Dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> where ſhe was ſeized on for His Majeſty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as lawfull price, being bound for <hi>Dover,</hi> or <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> This Ship had beene abroad 4. yeares, and was now returned homewards from the Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> laden with Bullion, Oyle, Couchanielle and other rich commodities to the value of 40000. l. at leaſt.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:24"/>
                  <p>The Treatie began at <hi>Uxbridge,</hi> wherein the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of His Majeſties moſt reall intentions and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of peace was very preſpicuous: For his Majeſtie did not only arme Commiſſioners, or any Tenne of them, with a very large and powerfull Commiſſion to treat of, conclude, and ſettle a firme peace in his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, but did alſo by Proclamation appoint a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Faſt on the fift day of <hi>February</hi> then next for a bleſſing on that treaty, with a forme of Common Prayer ſet forth by His Majeſty eſpeciall Command to be uſed in all Churches and Chappells within this Kingdome.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="February" type="month">
                  <head>February</head>
                  <p>9. Sir <hi>Walter Haſtings Governour</hi> of <hi>Portland</hi> Caſtle for His Majeſty, took the great fort of <hi>Weymouth,</hi> and within two dayes after Sir <hi>Lewis Dives</hi> took the middle fort and Towne of <hi>Weymouth,</hi> and in a skirmiſh there ſlew Major <hi>Sydenham</hi> (a forward enemy) with ſome others.</p>
                  <p>15. <hi>Rowdon</hi> houſe neare Chippenham in <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> (after nine dayes ſiege) was taken by His Majeſties Forces.</p>
                  <p>20. The Lord <hi>Macguire,</hi> an Iriſh Baron, was exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the common hang-man at <hi>Tyburne</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Parl. In the hiſtory of which execution re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in many of their owne Pamphlets, the reader may obſerve two queſtions asked by Maſter <hi>Gibbs,</hi> one of the Sheriffes of <hi>London,</hi> and anſwered by that Lord the very inſtant before his death.</p>
                  <p>The firſt was, whether he knew of any Commiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King had granted to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebells, for the commotion they had raiſed in <hi>Ireland.</hi> He anſwered, that he never knew, nor heard of any: the ſecond was; whether there was not ſome agreement made by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Commiſſioners, before the Rebellion firſt brake out, with the Recuſants in <hi>England?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:24"/>
                  <p>He anſwered, that to his Knowledge, there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any one in <hi>England,</hi> either Catholique or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, that knew of it, but one, and he was an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man, and a Proteſtant, and he came to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it by chance, not as he was an Actor in it.</p>
                  <p>Out of which, and out of that delivered by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> on the Scaffold immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately before his death, the world may evidently ſee His Majeſty irrefragably cleared, by two acts of the Parliaments owne cruelty, from two of the moſt ſcandalous aſperſions, by which the malice of theſe forgiving enemies hath from time to time endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make His Sacred Majeſtie odious to his People.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Salutem ex inimicis noſtris,</hi> may the King well ſay, ſeeing his enemies actions turned to his Juſtification, quite contrary to their intendments. The firſt was, an imagined inclination in His Majeſty to Popery; The ſecond a pretended Commiſſionating of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion. In the firſt, the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi> In this the Lord <hi>Macguire,</hi> both at their very dying houres, have rendred His Majeſty as innocent, as his enemies intended him odious. I ſay innocent, becauſe we know the worſt of Rebells cannot but credit thoſe perſons eſpecially, teſtifying at ſuch time when they were immediately after to give an account of all their Actions to the knower of all hearts. Nor can any one beleeve, but the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (who was dayly converſant with His Majeſty in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion) muſt needs know the very depth of his heart therein. And the Lord <hi>Macguire,</hi> (who was privy to the firſt motion of the Iriſh Rebellion) muſt likewiſe of neceſſity have known of the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion if any ſuch thing had been.</p>
                  <p>22. The Treaty at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> was broken up, though
<pb facs="tcp:42953:25"/> His Majeſty ſent a particular Meſſage, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners did earneſtly deſire that the ſame might be continued. In this treaty His Majeſties Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners condeſcended much, but thoſe of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> would abate nothing of the rigour of their unheard of Propoſitions, which was the cauſe the treaty tooke no better effect.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day was the Towne of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> (by treachery in the night) delivered to Colonell <hi>Mitton,</hi> the Parliaments Governour of <hi>Wem.</hi> Here you may ſee the Parliaments Maſterpiece, in hatching this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous plot in the time of Treaty, wherein they uſed the name of peace, only as a Maſque for their deſignes, but intended nothing leſſe.</p>
                  <p>25. Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale</hi> routed a great body of the Parl. forces conſiſting of at leaſt 1200. Horſe &amp; Dragoons, commanded by Colonell <hi>Roſſiter,</hi> a Scot, neare <hi>Melton Mowbray</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter ſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame day Colonell <hi>Roger Molineux,</hi> with a party of horſe from <hi>Mewarke</hi> took the Parl. Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee at <hi>Wirkſworth</hi> in <hi>Darby-ſhire,</hi> where they were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering Contribution.</p>
                  <p>26. Sir <hi>William</hi> and Sir <hi>Charles Compton</hi> brothers to the Noble Earle of <hi>Northampton</hi>) with three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred horſe, routed foure hundred of the Praliaments horſe of <hi>Northampton</hi> neare <hi>Daventry</hi> in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. In the latter end of this moneth, a party of His Majeſties Forces from <hi>Hereford,</hi> tooke Caſtle-ditch, (a Garriſon of the Parliaments) on the borders of that County.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>March</head>
                  <p>1. <hi>Pontfract</hi> Caſtle (that had been long beſieged, not without much loſſe to the Parl. by frequent ſallies made by the defendants and otherwiſe) was relieved by Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale,</hi> who there utterly defeated the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his whole Army.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:25"/>
                  <p>7. Major <hi>Abercromy</hi> a rebellious plundring Scot, was ſlaine neere <hi>Stratton Audley</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire,</hi> where his party of Horſe was routed, and 17. of his men and horſe taken priſoners, by a party from <hi>Borſtall</hi> houſe.</p>
                  <p>14. Col. <hi>Long</hi> the High Sherife of <hi>Wil ſhire,</hi> with his owne Regiment of Horſe onely, gallantly charged a great body of <hi>Wallers</hi> horſe neere the <hi>Deviſes,</hi> and did good ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cution on them; but being much over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered by the Parl. numbers, was at length taken Priſoner with ſome part of his Regiment, which was within few dayes after ſufficiently requited by the Lo: <hi>Goring,</hi> who took above 700. of <hi>Wallers</hi> Horſe in thoſe parts.</p>
                  <p>15. A party of His Majeſties Horſe from <hi>Pontfract</hi> Caſtle fell on Col. <hi>Brandlings</hi> Quarters at <hi>Badſworth,</hi> 4. miles from <hi>Doncaſter,</hi> took 67. priſoners, whereof 13. Officers, 130. Horſe, and 1000. l. in money.</p>
                  <p>18. The Earle of <hi>Northampton</hi> with his 3. young brothers (in all whom Gallantry is hereditary) routed a great body of the <hi>Northampton</hi> Horſe neere <hi>Althrop</hi> in that County.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day <hi>Beeſton</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> was relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by P. <hi>Ruperts</hi> approach into thoſe parts.</p>
                  <p>24. The Lower Members at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> vote the Clauſe for preſervation of His Majeſties Perſon to be left out in Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax</hi> his Commiſſion.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Thus doe the members</head>
                     <item>1. Sweare to live and dye with their owne General <hi>Eſſex,</hi> yet upon ſecond thoughts, they diſoblige themſelves from that oath, and caſhiere him of his Command.</item>
                     <item>2. Covenant to preſerve His Majeſties Perſon and Authority, and yet afterwards authorize Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax</hi> to kill him if he can.</item>
                     <item>2. They vow to maintain the Proteſtant Religion,
<pb facs="tcp:42953:26"/> yet condemne the eſſentiall parts thereof, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce irreligion and profaneneſſe.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Now tell me, Reader, what Tropologicall ſenſe can ſave this jugling from flat and literall Perjury? not all the addition of their Abrogative to their Legiſlative power; For this is indeed to abrogate Chriſtianity as well as Loyalty out of the World: To give leave to kill the Kings Perſon in the field, and yet to cheat men into a conceipt of preſerving His Majeſty in <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Lenthalls</hi> Chaire: To make the world beleeve they are Proteſtants, when they permit and authorize an illiterate Aſſembly of Non-Divines to diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the 39. Articles, diſpute about expunging the fift Article of the Apoſtles Creed: To antiquate the Lords Prayer out of the Church Service, and turne out the long-ſetled Service of Common-Prayer out of the Church, to give way to a long-winded extemporary non-ſenſe in the roome thereof.</p>
                  <q>O tempora! O mores!</q>
                  <p>Are not theſe fine Law-makers, who violate the Lawes of God and holy Church, as well as thoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were borne unto, to make way for their owne <hi>Chymeraes?</hi> Would not any true Zelot pawne his ſoule upon theſe mens conſciences, who make no conſcience of breaking their owne oathes? Would not any wiſe man melt his Fortunes to maintaine theſe mens Cauſe, who have no cauſe for what they doe? Yes, he that could be made to beleeve Perjury were Fidelity; Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Loyalty; Blaſpemy, Sanctity; Athieſme, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; the Speakers Cuſhion, the Kings Majeſtie; may likewiſe poſſibly beleeve that theſe Members intended the Churches, Kings, and Commmon-wealths good.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1647" type="year">
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:26"/>
               <head>Anno 1645.</head>
               <p>25. The Lord <hi>Goring</hi> routed a Party of the Parl. horſe at <hi>Pitmaſter</hi> neare <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet-ſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="April" type="month">
                  <head>Aprill</head>
                  <p>1. Major Generall Sir <hi>Jo. Digby</hi> with a Brigade of horſe and Dragoones beat up the Parl. Quarters at and about <hi>Wincaunton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. A party of the Lord <hi>Gorings</hi> horſe routed Col. <hi>Pophams</hi> Regiment in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>14. The ſiege of <hi>High-archall</hi> in <hi>Shrop-ſhire</hi> raiſed.</p>
                  <p>19. A party of His Majeſties from <hi>Newark</hi> tooke the Fort at <hi>Nottingham bridge,</hi> by Scalado.</p>
                  <p>22. Colonell <hi>Maſſeys</hi> forces were totally routed by Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> at <hi>Ledbury</hi> in <hi>Hereford-ſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>23. Major generall <hi>Laughorne</hi> lying at the ſiege of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> Emblin in <hi>Carmarthenſhire</hi> was totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated by His Maj. forces Commanded by Col. (now Lord) <hi>Gerard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>24 Colonell <hi>Cromwell</hi> (the Independent Generall) routed a party of His Majeſties horſe neare <hi>Iſlip,</hi> took divers Priſoners, and about 200. horſe. And no ſooner ſummoned <hi>Blechington</hi> houſe, but it was delivered up to him by Col. <hi>Windebank</hi> the Governour, who was ſoone after condemned by a Councell of War at <hi>Oxford</hi> and there ſhot to death in the Caſtle Yard.</p>
                  <p>26. The Garriſon of <hi>Farringdon</hi> loſt ſome few horſe and men, through the indiſcretion of a Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                  <p>30. <hi>Cromwell</hi> aſſaulted His Majeſties Garriſon of <hi>Farrington,</hi> but was repulſed with the loſſe of neare 200. of his men, beſides what were wounded and taken priſoners.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:27"/>
                  <p>7. His Majeſty martched from <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the ſame day the Lord <hi>Goring</hi> routed a ſtrong party of <hi>Cromwells</hi> horſe neare unto <hi>Newbridge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the begining of this Moneth that unheard of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie was put into practice in and about <hi>London</hi> by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perſons, men and women appointed and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to inveigle and entice young Children from their Parents, and without their knowledge, and ſo convay them on Ship-board to be ſold, or tranſported to new Plantations the Lord knowes where. This ſo much diſcontented the People, that the Houſes at <hi>VVeſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> were glad to diſavow the thing, and forthwith make an Order againſt it.</p>
                  <p>11. <hi>Taunton</hi> relieved by the Parl. forces.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day His Majeſties Forces made a gallant ſally from <hi>Scarborough</hi> Caſtle, wounded Sir <hi>Joh. Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drum,</hi> that commanded the ſiege, whereof he dyed, flew Col: Cockeram, Lievtenant Colonell <hi>Stanley,</hi> Major <hi>Dent,</hi> Capt. <hi>Percy,</hi> and 50. others, whereof moſt commanders, and tooke divers priſoners: On His Majeſties part were ſlaine Capt. <hi>Gower</hi> and ſome foure Common ſouldiers.</p>
                  <p>Soone after Captaine <hi>Zachary</hi> that Commanded one of the Ships in the Harbour for the Parliament, received a ſhot from the Caſtle whereof he dyed.</p>
                  <p>15. <hi>Hawksley</hi> houſe a Garriſon of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>VVorceſter-ſhire</hi> was ſurrendred to His Majeſtie at mercy only, and the houſe afterward ſlighted.</p>
                  <p>This done His Majeſty martched with His Army towards <hi>Cheſter,</hi> which had beene long beſieged by Sir <hi>VVilliam Brereton,</hi> but before His Majeſtie came within twenty miles of it, the Parliament raiſed their ſiege.</p>
                  <p>22. Sir <hi>Thomas Fairſax</hi> ſate downe before <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:27"/>
                  <p>23, <hi>Godſtow</hi> houſe quitted and ſlighted, and ſome houſes fired by the owner, <hi>M. David Waltar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>26. <hi>Maſſy</hi> ſurpriſed <hi>Eveſholme</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire,</hi> a Garriſon of His Majeſties.</p>
                  <p>30. His Majeſties Army ſate downe before <hi>Leiceſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>31. This morning <hi>Leiceſter</hi> was taken by ſtorme, and in it the whole Committee, &amp;c. And the ſame day the Parl. quitted their ſeverall Garriſons of <hi>Bagworth, Colehorton, Kirby-bellowes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Burleigh.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="June" type="month">
                  <head>June</head>
                  <p>2. Whilſt His Majeſties Army was thus buſied at <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> (the Parl. Generall) continued blocking up of <hi>Oxford,</hi> though f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uitl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſly, for by ſeverall ſallies thence, he loſt many of his men, and eſpecially this morning, when the Governour Col: <hi>William Legg</hi> with 1000. Horſe and Foot fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Parl. Guard at <hi>Heddington</hi> Hill, where they took and killed all their Muſquetiers, ſave one: their Horſe (not daring to withſtand them) ran all ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully away, and left their Foot to ſhift for themſelves. Theſe miſerable wretches had ſome two houres before moſt wickedly railed againſt the King and Queenes Majeſty, which much incenſed the Oxford Horſe.</p>
                  <p>4. Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> (weary of ſuch hot ſervice before <hi>Oxford</hi>) aſſaulted <hi>Borſtall</hi> houſe, (which he had cloſely ſurrounded the firſt of this month) but was bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten off with the loſſe of above 300. of his men.</p>
                  <p>6. There fell a ſtrange ſtorme of haile in that part of <hi>Leiceſter ſhire,</hi> which is in and about <hi>Loughborow:</hi> ſome of the haile-ſtones were as big as ſmall Hens egges, &amp; the leaſt as big as Muſquet-bullets: It deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Corne and did much hurt in that part of the Country where it fell.</p>
                  <p>9. His Majeſties forces encountered a body of the Parliament forces neare <hi>Stokeſey</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> but being over-powred, were forced to retreat with
<pb facs="tcp:42953:28"/> the loſſe of Sir <hi>Wil. Croft,</hi> a gallant Gentleman and ſome others.</p>
                  <p>14. Was the fatall battaile at <hi>Naesby</hi> downe in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> where His Majeſties Army (till then victorious) was now by the incertainty of Warre much worſted, his Infantry, Ordnance and Carriages loſt: Some have blamed Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> there, for preferring his owne raſh violence, before the reſult of a Councell of Warre, how deſerved I know not: However, I am ſure, there was a neceſſity of the one, not of the other: For, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> held, and that truly, <hi>Councell is as neceſſary in warre, as Pbyſitians in time of ſickneſſe.</hi> The whole number on both ſides ſlaine was conceived not to exceed 400. but more wounded. Above all, the Parl. cruelty was remarkable, in killing upon cold blood at leaſt 100. women, whereof many of quality, being Commanders wives, and far more moſt miſerably wounded; and this done under pretence that they were Iriſh women.</p>
                  <p>18. <hi>Leiceſter</hi> was re-taken by the Parl. upon Artl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; which were moſt perſidiouſly broken. The ſame day Capt. <hi>Wright</hi> (from <hi>Newarke</hi>) routed 200. of the Parl. Horſe at <hi>Ryby</hi> in <hi>Lincolneſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>27. <hi>Highworth</hi> yeelded to the Parl. who preſently made Sutling houſes, Stables, and (oh horrible to think of!) Houſes of Office within and about the Church, broke downe, and watered their horſes in the Font.</p>
                  <p>28. The City of <hi>Carlile</hi> was delivered to the Scots, (after it had been gallantly deſended 42. weeks) upon very honourable conditions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="July" type="month">
                  <head>July</head>
                  <p>2. <hi>Taunton</hi> the ſecond time relieved by the Parl:</p>
                  <p>4. Sir <hi>Will. Vaughan</hi> beat up the Par. Quarters neer Bramcroft Caſtle in Shropſhire. And</p>
                  <p>5. Routed the Beſiegers of <hi>High-Archall,</hi> killed 100
<pb facs="tcp:42953:28"/> of them, and took 400. Priſoners, with all their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and baggage.</p>
                  <p>10. A Brigade of the Lord <hi>Gorings</hi> Army worſted at <hi>Langport,</hi> being over-powred by the Parl. and ſo forced to a diſorderly retreat, with the loſſe of 300<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> men, amongſt whom was that gallant and reſolute Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Sir <hi>John Digby,</hi> who there received a hurt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he ſhortly after dyed.</p>
                  <p>16. <hi>Chippenham,</hi> a new erected Garriſon of the Parl. in <hi>VViltſhire,</hi> was taken by Col. <hi>Long.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame day a party from <hi>Newarke</hi> ſurpriſed <hi>VVel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck</hi> houſe.</p>
                  <p>21. <hi>Pontfract</hi> Caſtle, after three months ſiege, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred upon honourable conditions.</p>
                  <p>22. <hi>Bridgewater</hi> aſſaulted, and taken by Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax,</hi> not without much loſſe of blood to the Aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, and of goods to the poore Townes-people.</p>
                  <p>25. <hi>Searborough</hi> delivered (upon conditions) to the Parl.</p>
                  <p>30. The city of <hi>Bath</hi> ſurrendred.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="August" type="month">
                  <head>Auguſt</head>
                  <p>1. A party of Horſe from <hi>Newarke</hi> tooke <hi>Torkeſey</hi> houſe in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> by ſcalado.</p>
                  <p>4. The club-men of <hi>Dorſetſhire</hi> diſperſed.</p>
                  <p>8. Captaine <hi>Allen</hi> and his whole Troop were taken on the borders of <hi>Lincolneſhire,</hi> by a party from <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voire</hi> Caſtle.</p>
                  <p>15. <hi>Sherburne</hi> Caſtle aſſaulted and taken by the Parl.</p>
                  <p>17. The Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſe</hi> utterly defeated an Army conſiſting of at leaſt 12000 Scots in <hi>Kilſeith</hi> field neere <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> ſlew 3500<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> took 2000. Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>20. <hi>Nunny</hi> caſtle in <hi>Sommerſet-ſhire</hi> ſurrendred to the Parl.</p>
                  <p>24. <hi>Hunting don</hi> taken by His Maj. Forces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="September" type="month">
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:29"/>
                  <head>September</head>
                  <p>2. The Scots (upon His Majeſties approach with His Army) raiſed their ſiege from before <hi>Hereford,</hi> (where they had laine five weeks before) and haſtned away, plundring every body where they came.</p>
                  <p>6. His Majeſties Forces from <hi>Oxford,</hi> beat up the Parl. Quarters at <hi>Tame,</hi> killed divers, took priſoner Adjutant Generall <hi>Puide,</hi> with divers other Officers &amp; common Souldiers. This <hi>Puide</hi> within three dayes after he was brought to Oxford had leave to depart up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Parol; yet wanted the civility either to returne himſelfe, or to releaſe the Gentleman (or any other) that he promiſed in exchange for him. Such and no better is the faith and humanity of their Souldiers. They took alſo three Colours, and above 250. Horſe.</p>
                  <p>9. Maſter <hi>Strode,</hi> one of the five Members, and one of the principall promoters of this unnaturall warre, died of a Peſtilentiall Fever, to ſay no more of it.</p>
                  <p>11. <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> part of it, won by aſſault, the reſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred (by P. <hi>Rupert</hi>) upon Conditions, after 3. weeks ſiege.</p>
                  <p>13. A Brigade of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſe</hi> his Forces received a defeat, at <hi>Philip—haugh</hi> in <hi>Tividale</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> being the firſt cleare defeat that ever that noble Marqueſſe, or any conſiderable part of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my received ſince the beginning of this War.</p>
                  <p>22. The Caſtle of the <hi>Devizes</hi> (in <hi>Wiltſhire</hi>) was ſurrendred to the Parl. upon Conditions, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>24. Five thouſand of His Majeſties Horſe encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred a far greater Body of the Parl. Forces at <hi>Routon</hi>-heath neere <hi>Weſtcheſter,</hi> then beſieged. In this fight His Majeſties Army was worſted, having loſt that noble and valiant Gentleman, the Lord <hi>Bernard Steward,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lichfield,</hi> and ſome others. The Parl. here (as in moſt other places) loſt no men of quality, having very few or none in their Army to loſe.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:29"/>
                  <p>26. <hi>Barckley</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Glouceſter-ſhire</hi> was ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the Parl. upon Conditions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="October" type="month">
                  <head>October</head>
                  <p>1. <hi>Sandall</hi> Caſtle in <hi>York ſhire,</hi> after a long ſiege, ſurrendred to the Parl. upon Conditions, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>6. <hi>Wincheſter</hi> Caſtle was likewiſe delivered upon Compoſition, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>14. <hi>Baſing</hi> houſe was taken by Storme, the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants not having a ſufficient number within to Man their Works, ſo that they were wearyed out with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall duty. Here was the truly loyall and noble Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> (that had ſo long and gallantly defended his owne houſe) taken priſoner, with about 200. others, and at leaſt 100. of the defendants flaine, many whereof in cold blood: the murtherers uſing theſe words, <hi>Curſed be he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>15. A Brigade of His Majeſties Horſe martched Northward, under the Command of the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> and Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdall,</hi> ſurpriſed 800. of the foot at <hi>Sherburne</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> but before they had diſpoſed of the Priſoners and Armes, a freſh party en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered them, reſcued the Priſoners, diſordered His Majeſties Forces, ſlew Sir <hi>Richa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d Hutton</hi> and divers others.</p>
                  <p>16. <hi>Tiverton</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> aſſaulted and taken by the Parliament forces.</p>
                  <p>11. <hi>Langford</hi> houſe in Wiltſhire ſurrendred.</p>
                  <p>27. <hi>Shelford</hi> houſe in <hi>Nottinghamſhire</hi> taken by ſtorme, the valiant Governour (Colonell <hi>Stanhop</hi>) defended it, even, to the laſt man, himſelfe and neere 200. others were ſlaine by the mercilefle enemies, after they had entred the houſe, having firſt loſt about 60 of their men in the aſſault.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="November" type="month">
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:30"/>
                  <head>November</head>
                  <p>5. <hi>Bolton</hi> Caſtie in <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> ſurrendred to the Parl. upon conditions.</p>
                  <p>16. <hi>Beeſton</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> (after long ſiege) was likewiſe ſurrendred to the Parliament upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</p>
                  <p>22. The ſtables and Out-works of <hi>Belvoire</hi> Caſtle were gained by ſtorme, in which action the Parl. loſt 100. of their men, and more wounded, the defendants retreating into the Caſtle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="December" type="month">
                  <head>December.</head>
                  <p>1. The Houſe of Commons at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> voted the King to confer ſeverall Honours upon ſeverall Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of each Houſe, and (<hi>inter alios</hi>) a Dukedome on the E. of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and the heires Males of his Body lawfully begotten.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Latham</hi> houſe (that had ſo long and gallantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it ſelfe, and ſo often offended the enemy) was ſurrondred to them upon conditions.</p>
                  <p>5. His Majeſty ſent to the Parliament at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> to deſire that the Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> Earle of <hi>Southampton,</hi> Maſter <hi>Aſhburnham,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Palmer,</hi> might have a ſafe conduct to bring propoſitions of Peace.</p>
                  <p>15. His Majeſty ſent a ſecond Letter, with the moſt powerfull perſwaſions immaginable, that a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct might be granted according to his deſire in his former Letter, but both had one deniall in a letter of the 25. of <hi>December.</hi> The ſame day was the Loyall Citie of <hi>Hereford</hi> (by the perfidiouſneſſe of ſome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and the bribery of others without) delivered into the hands of the Par. Forces, without any ſiege, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt any blood-ſhed, whereby the Perſons and Goods of many Gentlemen of Quality, and other loyall Subjects, fell into the hands of the mercileſſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:30"/>
                  <p>22. The Lords at Weſtminſter (to the eternall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of that houſe) put it to the Vote, Whether Chriſtmas day ſhould be kept or no: For truly to blor out that, and the memory of Chriſts Paſſion, is the neareſt way to introduce Judaiſme.</p>
                  <p>26. His Majeſty ſent a third Meſſage, wherein he offered to repaire perſonally to <hi>London,</hi> for concluding a peace, but this found no better acceptance then the two former.</p>
                  <p>29. His Majeſty ſent an Anſwer to the Parl. Letter of the 25. of this moneth; and did then againe uſe the beſt perſwaſions he could to beget in them admittance of a perſonall Treaty; both which laſt received a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall from the Parliament by a Letter dated <hi>Jan.</hi> 13. 1645.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="January" type="month">
                  <head>January</head>
                  <p>1. The <hi>Newarkers</hi> made a gallant Sally upon <hi>Pointz</hi> his Quarters at <hi>ſtoke,</hi> killed and tooke above 220. of his men, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>14. His Majeſty ſent a fift Meſſage, inviting to Peace.</p>
                  <p>16. The ſiege before <hi>Plymouth</hi> raiſed.</p>
                  <p>17. His Majeſty ſent an Anſwer to the Parl. Letter of the 13. of <hi>Janu.</hi> with many gracious expreſſions of his deſire of Peace.</p>
                  <p>18. <hi>Dartmouth</hi> was taken by Sir <hi>T. Fairfax,</hi> part of it by ſtorme, and part by compoſition.</p>
                  <p>20. Sir <hi>John Cansfield</hi> beat up the Parl. Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at <hi>Marlborough.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame day a party from <hi>Aſhby-de-la-Zouche</hi> tooke <hi>Aſtley</hi> Caſtle, in <hi>Warwickeſhire,</hi> by Scalado.</p>
                  <p>24. His Majeſty ſent a 7. Meſſage in fuller An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Parliaments Letter of the 13. of this moneth, with earneſt deſire of ſatisfactory Anſwers to his former Letters; the aime of all which ſtill levelled at the peace and welfare of this bleeding Kingdome:</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:31"/>
                  <p>29. His Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſty ſent an eight Meſſage to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, with many gracious condeſcendings for Peace, but their eares were ſtill deafe to ſuch pious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p>30. A party from <hi>Ragland</hi> Caſtle, took the town of <hi>Carilon</hi> in <hi>Monmouthſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="February" type="month">
                  <head>February</head>
                  <p>1. The ſame party from <hi>Ragland</hi> took the towne of <hi>Newport</hi> in that Countie.</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>Belvon</hi> Caſtle ſurrendred to the Parl. upon ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Conditions, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day was <hi>Weſtcheſter</hi> ſurrendred upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>6. <hi>Dunſter</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Summerſetſhire</hi> relieved by Major Generall <hi>Webbe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>7. A partie of His Majeſties forces entred the town of <hi>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ham</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> took Colonell <hi>Butler</hi> the Governour, two Commit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee men and ſome others, and thence martched to <hi>Corſe</hi> Caſtle there beſieged, which they releeved, tooke a morter peece of the enemies, and made a ſafe retreate without any loſſe.</p>
                  <p>15. A little but ſharpe encounter happened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a party of His Majeſties forces from <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tbury</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and a like party of the Parl. from <hi>Barton</hi> houſe in <hi>Darbiſhire,</hi> wherein after above halfe an houres diſpute, ſome ſlaine and many hurt on each ſide, the Parl. for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were routed, and many of them taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
                  <p>16. <hi>Torrington</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> entred by the Parl. forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</p>
                  <p>18. A party of the Parl. forces neare <hi>uttoxeter,</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> were routed by His Majeſties For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                  <p>26. His Majeſtie ſent a ninth Letter to <hi>weſiminſter</hi> to deſire an Anſwer of his former letter, ſtill preſſing for Peace.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:31"/>
                  <p>The ſame day <hi>Corſe</hi> Caſtle (but lately releeved) was delivered into the hands of the Parliament by the treachery and perfidiouſneſſe of one Lievtenant Col. <hi>Pitman.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>March</head>
                  <p>2. A party of His Majeſties forces from <hi>Oxford</hi> entred the towne of <hi>Abbingdon,</hi> ſeized upon the Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Magazine, yet for want (only) of a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen ſpades were forced to retreat, with ſome priſoners, and few ſlaine on either ſide. Tis known who was too blame.</p>
                  <p>14. The Lord <hi>Hopton</hi> being much overpowred by the Parliaments Forces in the Weſt, was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pt of conditions for the disbanding his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>21. The Lord <hi>Aſtley</hi> commanded a Brigade of horſe and foot from <hi>VVorceſte ſhire,</hi> which were inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for <hi>Oxford,</hi> were ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t upon by an aggregate body of the Parliaments Forces on the edge of <hi>Glouceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> and defeated, the foot moſt taken, with my Lord himſelfe, and ſome of the horſe, the remainder eſcaped and got to <hi>Oxford.</hi> Thus had His Majeſty two Armies defeated in leſle then a fortnight. Yet we are confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent when Almighty God have ſufficienly puniſht the Sinnes of this Nation, he will in his good time reſtore a pious King to his juſt Rights, and this bleeding King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to Peace and Union in deſpight of all Sectaries and Opponents.</p>
                  <p>23. His Majeſty (never weary in acting any thing tending to Peace) ſent his tenth Meſſage to this effect, that in caſe he might have the faith of his two houſes of Parliament for the preſervation of his Honour, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Eſtate, and that liberty might be given to all thoſe that doe and have adhered to His Majeſty to enjoy their eſtates, without any ſequeſtration, or being compelled to take any Oathes, not enjoyned by Law,
<pb facs="tcp:42953:32"/> he would then disband his forces, diſmantle his Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, return to and reſide with his two Houſes of Parl. &amp;c. And could more be offered by, or expected from a gracious King?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1648" type="year">
               <head>Anno 1646.</head>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>March</head>
                  <p>25. The City of <hi>Worceſter</hi> was ſummoned by Sir <hi>Will. Brereton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the ſame day was <hi>Dennington</hi> Caſtle ſurrendred to the Parl. upon Articles.</p>
                  <p>27. <hi>Newarke</hi> ſummoned by the Engliſh and Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Forces.</p>
                  <p>30. An Anſwer was agreed on by the Houſes to be ſent to His Majeſty, being a flat denyall to his Tenth moſt gracious Meſſage of the 23. of <hi>March,</hi> wherein they told the King, <hi>That it would be unſafe for Him, or them, to returne to weſtminſter, untill He had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Propoſitions, which they were fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now can any man imagine, that theſe men ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the Honour and ſafety of His Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the reſtoring of Him to His juſt Rights, or (their maine pretence) the bringing of His Majeſties Perſon from among his evill Counſellors; or had the leaſt thought of compoſing theſe unhappy differences, and of ſetling the Kingdome in peace, when after ſo many gracious Meſſages ſent unto them, (the worſt of men) by Him, (the beſt of Kings) and therein ſo many more then faire propoſals, and condeſcendings for the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a happy and laſting peace; that yet theſe men ſhould rerurne Him a flat denyall for comming to Weſtminſter, untill He had aſſented to the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which they were a framing; that is, as much as if they had ſaid, Untill He had granted them they knew
<pb facs="tcp:42953:32"/> not what; for as yet neither they themſelves (much leſſe His Majeſty) knew what thoſe Propoſitions were; as their owne words import.</p>
                  <p>31. And in caſe His Majeſty ſhould reſolve to throw himſelfe into their armes, by comming to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> without their knowledge and conſent, (as what would not His Majeſty have ever done for to beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t a good underſtanding betwixt Him and His People, and to manifeſt the ſincerity of His endeavours, for obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace?) to prevent that, they voted, <hi>That if the King</hi> (contrary to their ſaid Anſwer) <hi>ſhould come, or attempt to come</hi> (mark the heighth of their pride) <hi>within the Lines of Communication; that then the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Militia of London ſhould have power, and were thereby enjoyned to apprehend and ſecure</hi> (that is, impriſon) <hi>ſuch as ſhould come with him, to prevent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort unto him, and to ſecure his Perſon, (i. e.</hi> to commit him (cloſe priſoner) to the Tower.</p>
                  <p>And the more to manifeſt their inveterate hatred and malice to His Majeſty, and all ſuch as had beene loyall to Him, the ſame day they thundred out another Order, commanding all men that had borne Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, to depart the City of London, and Lines of Communication, by the 6. of April fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, or otherwiſe to be proceeded againſt as Spies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="April" type="month">
                  <head>April</head>
                  <p>1. The Neworkers made a gallant and ſucceſſefull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lly upon the enemy before that towne; wherein they ſlew and drowned many of their beſt men, and tooke divers priſoners.</p>
                  <p>3. And leſt ſuch of His majeſties friends, as they had baniſhnd by their laſt mentioned Order, ſhould addreſſe themſelves to His majeſty, or the Queene, or to any other of the Nobility, for their reliefe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: The Parl. at Weſtminſter paſſed a bloody Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, for eſtabliſhing a Court martiall in London;
<pb facs="tcp:42953:33"/> wherein they gave power to Commiſſioners, or any twelve of them, (a fit Jury) to puniſh with death all ſuch as ſhould voluntarily repaire unto the perſon of the King, or Queene, or Lords of the Councell, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>7. And that nothing which was either good or holy might eſcape the effects of their cruelty, they ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Ordered, <hi>That the Braſſe Statue, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>faced Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents in the Church of VVindſor, ſhould be ſold</hi> (to Tinkers,) <hi>and the proceed thereof paid to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Souldiers of VVindſor Caſtle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>8. <hi>Ruthen</hi> Caſtle, &amp;c. ſurrendred to <hi>Mitton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. <hi>Exeter</hi> ſurrendred upon Articles.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day <hi>Lichſield</hi> Cloſe was ſummoned; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a gallant and reſolute Anſwer was returned by Sir <hi>Thomas Tildſley,</hi> Col. <hi>Baggot,</hi> and the reſt of that Loyall Garriſon.</p>
                  <p>14. <hi>Barnſtaple</hi> ſurrendred Towne and Caſtle.</p>
                  <p>15. S. <hi>Michaels</hi> mount yeelded.</p>
                  <p>21. <hi>Barnſtaple</hi> Fort ſurrendred.</p>
                  <p>25. <hi>Dunſtar</hi> Caſtle and <hi>Aburſtwith</hi> yeelded to the Parliam.</p>
                  <p>26. <hi>VVoodſtock</hi> mannour, a place naturally ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that it was ſcarce capable of Fortification: Yet by the excellent skill, care, and induſtry of Capt. <hi>Samuel Fawcet,</hi> a Gentleman of unqueſtionable worth and fidelity, ſo ſtrengthned it by Art, where Nature had been deficient, and ſo judiciouſly and valorouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it againſt the Enemy, that he killed many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of them before the Workes; ſallyed frequently upon them, with great ſucceſſe and ſafety; took a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and reſolutely withſtood them, till he had not halfe a barrell of powder left him: yet nevertheleſſe had reſolved to have left his bones there, had not His Majeſty ſent Commiſſioners to treat for him with the Enemy, for the ſurrender of the Garriſon, which this day was delivered upon Articles.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:33"/>
                  <p>27. This morning early His maieſty (being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to attempt comming to <hi>London,</hi> or <hi>VVeſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and all his meſſages, and propoſalls for peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing denyed, and an Army ready to inviron him within the Walls of <hi>Oxford</hi>) was enforced of two inevitable evills to chuſe which he conceived the leſſer, <hi>viz.</hi> to flye to the Scottiſh. Army (then before <hi>Newarke</hi>) for protection, thinking (by that meanes) to preſerve his life, and more eaſily to compoſe theſe unhapy diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences betwixt him and his Subiects.</p>
                  <p>About the ſame time that perfidious Prelate, and ſhame of the Clergy, <hi>williams,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate-Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop</hi> of <hi>Yorke,</hi> deſerted His Majeſty, put a Garriſon in, and fortified his Houſe at <hi>Purin,</hi> neare <hi>Conway</hi> in <hi>wales,</hi> and proteſted againſt the Kings Party, which he had formerly ſworne to maintain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="May" type="month">
                  <head>May</head>
                  <p>2. The Parliaments Army commanded by Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> the ſecond time Leagured before <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4. The Treaty began at <hi>Newarke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame day (the Houſes not being yet certainly informed where His Majeſty was gone, and ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Him to be in <hi>London,</hi> concealed by the Major or ſome other honeſt Citizen) to the end His Majeſty ſhould not finde any place whereon (quietly) to reſt his head, they paſſed an Order, and publiſht it by beat of Drumme throughout the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter;</hi> That what perſon ſoever ſhould harbour, and conceale, or know of the harbouring or concealing of the Kings Perſon, and ſhould not reveale it immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to the Speakers of both Houſes, ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt as a Traitor to the Common-wealth, forfeit his whole Eſtate, and die without mercy.</p>
                  <p>Was it ever heard of before, (ſpeake you Lawyers) that to harbour the Kings Perſon, was, or could be Treaſon?</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:34"/>
                  <p>5. But (whilſt they were ſearching of the Lord <hi>Majors</hi> Houſe for him (an act beyond preſident, wherein the Honour of the Citie is yet not a little concerned) His Majeſty arrived at Southwell; and from thence was he conducted into the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army.</p>
                  <p>6. Upon notice whereof, the Commons voted that the Scottiſh Commiſſioners, and the Generall of the Scottiſh Army ſhould be deſired, that His Majeſties perſon be diſpoſed of as both houſes ſhall deſire and direct: And that he be thence diſpoſed of and ſent (a Priſoner) to <hi>Warwick</hi> Caſtle. And further Orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that Maſter <hi>Aſhburnham,</hi> and the reſt that came with the King into the Scottiſh Quarters, ſhould be ſent for as Delinquents, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>8. <hi>Banbury</hi> was ſurrendred upon Articles.</p>
                  <p>9. <hi>Newarke</hi> (after 6. weekes ſiege) delivered: upon this the Scottiſh Army drew off from before <hi>Newarke</hi> and retreated about foure miles and the King with them in the head of their Army.</p>
                  <p>11. <hi>Oxford, Borſtall</hi> houſe, <hi>Radcot</hi> and <hi>Walling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> were ſummoned by the Parl. forces.</p>
                  <p>13 His Majeſty came into <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>16. <hi>Hartleborough</hi> Caſtle ſurrendred to Colonell <hi>Morgan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>18. His Majeſty (after he had withdrawne himſelfe to the Scottiſh Army) for to ſecure His Perſon, ſent His eleventh moſt Gracious Meſſage, wherein he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to the two Houſes, all the wayes, and meanes poſſible, for the ſpeedy finiſhing ſo Pious &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a worke, as that of ſetling Peace within His Kingdomes: And particularly deſired that they would take the advice of the Divines of both Kingdomes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> As for the Militia, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was pleaſed to have it ſetled, as was offered at the Treaty at <hi>Uxbridge</hi> for ſeven yeares: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:42953:34"/> the Warre in <hi>Ireland,</hi> His majeſty would doe whatſoever was poſſible for him to give full ſatisfaction therein, &amp;c. His majeſty being reſolved to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the Parliament, in every thing that ſhould be for the happineſſe of His ſubjects, and for the removing of all unhappy differences, which had produced ſo ſad effects, &amp;c. And that He would take a ſpeedy courſe for eaſing and quieting his afflicted people, by ſatisfiing the publique debts, by disbanding of all Armies, and whatſoever elſe ſhould be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conducible to that end, that ſo all hindrances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing removed, He might returne to His Parliament with mutuall comfort: And being deſirous to ſhun tho further effuſion of blood, and to evidence His reall intentions to peace, His majeſty further ſignified unto them that he was willing, that his forces in &amp; about <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> ſhould be disbanded, &amp; the fortifications of the City diſmantled, they receiving Honourable conditions, which being granted to the Towne and forces there, His majeſty would give the like Order to the reſt of the Garriſons.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day began the Treaty at <hi>Marſton</hi> a mile from <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>19. It was voted; <hi>That this Kingdome</hi> (the Parl. at <hi>Weſtminſter) had no further need of the Army of their Brethren</hi> (in Rebellion) <hi>the Scots in this Kingdome.</hi> And further, that the ſumme of 100000. I. ſhould be advanced, and paid to the Scottiſh Army, &amp;c. (for Invading and Plundring the Kingdome, and for running away from <hi>Hereford,</hi> and <hi>Marſton-Moore.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>26. A Remonſtrance from the Lord <hi>Major,</hi> Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Common councell was preſented to the Houſes at <hi>VVeſtminſter</hi> which they promiſed to take into their Conſideration, in convenient time, but that times not come yet, <hi>March</hi> 25. 1647.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:35"/>
                  <p>4. A great defeat given unto the Scottiſh and Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh forces, by the Iriſh, neare unto <hi>Benburke</hi> in the County of <hi>Tyron,</hi> wherein the Lord Viſcount <hi>Mountgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery</hi> was taken priſoner, and his Lievtenant of Horſe deadly wounded: The Lord <hi>Blancy</hi> killed, above 5000. more drowned, and taken, with all their Amuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and about 5000. foot Armes, and moſt of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers killed, or taken.</p>
                  <p>6. <hi>Carnarvon</hi> Towne and Caſtle ſurrendred to the Parliament.</p>
                  <p>9. And ſtill to continue their wonted practice of indeavouring to make His majeſty odious to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; (notwithſtanding that His maj. had fully &amp; freely declared to the Scottiſh Army upon his comming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that his repaire to them; was purpoſely to compoſe the differences betwixt him and his Subjects, &amp;c. and to ſettle a firme Peace in theſe two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes) the Houſes at <hi>VVeſtminſter</hi> voted (1.) That His maieſty in going to the Scottiſh Army in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, thereby intended to prolong the Warres in this Kingdome. Now let any man judge whether theſe men aime at any thing more then the Ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of His maieſty? For, neither would they admit of his comming to <hi>London,</hi> or <hi>VVeſtminſter;</hi> Nor yet reliſh his going to the Scots; but tell the World it was to prolong the Warres.</p>
                  <p>(2.) That a declaration ſhould be drawne to ſet forth new Jealouſies and feares, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The ſame ninth day <hi>Ludlow</hi> was delivered upon Articles.</p>
                  <p>10. And now all the world may ſee and iudge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther His maieſty had any intention to prolong the Warres, when he ſent a warrant ſigned with his owne hand, and directed to the Governours of <hi>Oxford, Lichfield, VVorceſter,</hi> and <hi>VVallingford,</hi> and all other Commanders of any other Townes, Caſtles,
<pb facs="tcp:42953:35"/> or Forts within the Kingdome of England or Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Wales, requiring them upon honourable Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to quit the Townes, Caſtles, and Forts, and to disband all the Forces under their ſeverall commands. Now if disbanding of Forces, and quitting of Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be any meane or ſigne of prolonging the Warre, let thoſe of Bedlam determine, ſince thoſe at Weſtm. miſtake ſo groſty.</p>
                  <p>20. The Articles for the ſurrender of Oxford were concluded, and the Treaty ended.</p>
                  <p>24. <hi>Oxford</hi> (His Majeſties head Garriſon) and the famous Univerſity thereof, after 6. weeks ſiege, was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred upon Articles to the Army of the Independents under the Conduct of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax.</hi> Which Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles were afterwards moſt perfidiouſly broken, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by their Maſters (the Wiſe-men) at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By arreſting and impriſoning the Governour himſelfe, and divers others, for many weeks toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Compter and other priſons, contrary to the 7. Article.</item>
                     <item>2. By diſarming (maliciouſly) ſuch of the Officers and Soldiers of that Garriſon, &amp;c. as repaired to London, contrary to the 5. Article.</item>
                     <item>3. By baniſhing them 20 miles diſtance from the Lines of Communication, contrary to the ſaid 5. Article.</item>
                     <item>4. And laſtly, by not ſuffering any belonging to the ſocieties of the Innes of Court, Innes of Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or the Sergeants Inne, who had aſſiſted His Majeſty, according as they were bound both by Law and Conſcience, to be admitted to live in any of the ſaid Societies.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>30. One <hi>Morgan (alias Powel</hi>) who was formerly arraigned and convicted for a Prieſt of the Order of Saint <hi>Benedict,</hi> at the Kings Bench Barre,
<pb facs="tcp:42953:36"/> was drawne, hang'd and quartered.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="July" type="month">
                  <head>July</head>
                  <p>1. The Treaty began at <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame day His Highneſſe the Prince of Wales, being forced out of the Kingdome by the Parl. arrived at S. <hi>Jermans</hi> with about 200. attendants, where his Mother (the Queenes Majeſty) then was; being fled thither (long before) to ſave her life from the fury of thoſe creatures that had voted her a Traitor.</p>
                  <p>2. Ordered that all Papiſts and Iriſh ſhould be put out of the Lines of Communication of the city of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and all other Corporated places in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>3. Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> ſent the True (not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit) Great Seale of England, the Privy, Seale, the Signet Royall, the Seale of the K. Bench, the Seale of the Exchequer, the Seale of the Court of Wards, the Seale of the Admiralty and Navy, and the Sword to the Parl. at Weſtminſter. And (in great haſte) they Ordered, That all the ſaid Seales ſhould be forthwith broken in pieces, and that the Sword ſhould be kept ſafe in the Kings Wardrobe.</p>
                  <p>6. Ordered, that all (ſuch Godly and Learned) Miniſters that had adhered to His Majeſty, and beene ſequeſtred for their Malignancie, (i. e. Loyalty) ſhould be diſ-enabled from any Office, place or priviledge of the Miniſtery; That is, they, their wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, muſt firſt beg, and then ſtarve:</p>
                  <p>The ſame day they renewed their former vote; that this Kingdome had no more need of the Scottiſh Army, &amp;c. and that a Letter ſhould be ſent to the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to deſire them to withdraw their Army into <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>7. Sir <hi>Peter Killigrew</hi> (the State-Poſte) was ſent towards <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> with a Letter dated July 6. to His Majeſty, to deſire Him to give order to the Marqueſſe
<pb facs="tcp:42953:36"/> of <hi>Ormond</hi> to ſurrender <hi>Dublin</hi> up to the Parl. and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Garriſons in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>9. They Ordered that the honeſt and faithfull Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen Attendants upon the Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> ſhould be all diſcharged.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day Monſieur <hi>Bellieure</hi> (the French Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour) landed, and came to <hi>Greenwich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the ſame day <hi>Maſſey</hi> was ſworne a Member in the Houſe of Commons, and took his place in the Houſe. In the firſt Expedition againſt the Scots, he thought himſelfe highly advanced in being Capt. of the Pyoniers for 5. ſ. <hi>per diem,</hi> and then one might have ſpoke to him without a cringe: I wonder how a man muſt addreſſe himſelfe unto him now?</p>
                  <p>And this day alſo <hi>Montrill</hi> (the French Agent) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to His Majeſty from France, with a Letter from the Queene, wherein (as tis recorded in the London Newes-books) ſhe adviſed the King to make Peace with the three Kingdomes upon any termes, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Now is it not to be wondred at, with what impudence theſe malicious wretches dare tax Her Majeſty for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a meanes of this war; that know and acknowledge her thus piouſly adviſing the King (her Husband) to Peace?</p>
                  <p>10. Monſieur <hi>Bellieure</hi> (the French Ambaſſadour Extraordinary) came into London.</p>
                  <p>11. A moſt gracious Letter came from His Majeſty in anſwer to the Par. Letter of the 6. of July, wherein he granted all their deſires, touching the ſurrender of the Garriſons in Ireland.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day they committed <hi>John Lilburne</hi> cloſe Priſoner in the Tower.</p>
                  <p>14. Commiſſioners were ſent to His Majeſty at Newcaſtle, with the Parl. moſt unreaſonable and ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Propoſitions for Peace, being ſuch as are wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the Fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome,
<pb facs="tcp:42953:37"/> and which would abſolutely deprive His Majeſty of His Regall Power.</p>
                  <p>16. <hi>Lichfield</hi> Cloſe ſurrendred upon Articles.</p>
                  <p>17. Monſieur <hi>Bellieure</hi> was highly honoured with the deafe ears of the Parl. at Weſtminſt.</p>
                  <p>23. <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſurrendred upon Articles.</p>
                  <p>The ſame 13. day a Declaration was paſſed, and paſted upon every poſte, prohibiting all ſuch as had adhered to the King, to preſume to repaire to the Court, or to the Kings Perſon, &amp;c. and particularly that <hi>Edward Walker</hi> (the King thought him worthy (ſo doe all that know him rightly) to be called Sir <hi>Edward Walker</hi>) a dangerous Malignant, &amp;c. to be diſmiſſed and ſent away from about His majeſty. See what care they took to have none but—about Him.</p>
                  <p>24. The Prineeſſe <hi>Henrietta</hi> (having been long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of all things, even common neceſſaries, ſuitable to the quality of the Kings daughter, though the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, her evill Angell, had been often told of it) was happily conveyed away from Oatlands by the Lady <hi>Dalkeith,</hi> and carryed to the Queene her mother in France.</p>
                  <p>31. <hi>Gotheridge</hi> Caſtle in Wales ſurrendred.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="August" type="month">
                  <head>Auguſt</head>
                  <p>1. A Peace between the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Catholiques of <hi>Ireland</hi> proclaimed at <hi>Dublin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. The Commiſſioners received His Majeſties Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Anſwer touching the Parl. Propoſitions, &amp; took their leave of him. I did not heare that any of them kiſſed his hand—</p>
                  <p>5. <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> (the very ſame man that ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly uſed the Butchers wife by Smithfield Barres) had 200. 1. <hi>per annum</hi> Ordered him out of certaine Lands of Delinquents for publique and great ſervices: But the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> whilſt he lived would not ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:42953:37"/> him to enjoy it, for ſome reaſons beſt knowne to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Shortly after their Gen: <hi>Fairfax</hi> came to towne, and had ſlender thanks return'd him by ſome of the more factious Citizens: But the Houſe of Com. ordered him thanks, and a ſlender viſit. And (as a reward of his good ſervices) inſtead of an Army, gave him a Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade, and bad farewell to their Generall.</p>
                  <p>7. <hi>Ragland</hi> Caſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſummoned.</p>
                  <p>10. The Commiſſioners that carried the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to His Majeſty returned to <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>18. The French Ambaſſadours Letters ſeized on, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and read Publiquely in the Houſe of Commons. Will not <hi>France</hi> remember this?</p>
                  <p>The ſame day, were the true Great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and the reſt of His Majeſties Scales that were taken in <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſave only two, <hi>viz.</hi> the Privie Signet and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall Signet all broken and defaced by one <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Radley</hi> (a ſhirking fellow) now attendant on the Committee at <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> Hall in the preſence of all the Higher and Lower Kings at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Houſe.</p>
                  <p>13. The Silver of the broken Seales were beſtowed on the Speakers of both Houſes; which they formed into Plate: But I hardly beleeve they ever drank His Majeſties health in them.</p>
                  <p>17. Sir <hi>John Stowell</hi> (a rationall and reſolute Gentleman) only for deſirng to know hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Charge, and why he might not be admitted to his Compoſition, was Ordered to be ſent Priſoner to <hi>Newgate</hi> and that an Indictment ſhould be drawne up againſt him at the next Aſſizes, for aſſiſting His Majeſty againſt his enemies.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day <hi>Pendennis</hi> Caſtle was yeilded.</p>
                  <p>About this time <hi>Conoway</hi> town was taken by ſtorme. Where <hi>Mitton</hi> tyed many Engliſh and Iriſh back to
<pb facs="tcp:42953:38"/> back and threw them Over-board.</p>
                  <p>19. <hi>Ragland</hi> Caſtle ſurrendred.</p>
                  <p>28. It was Ordred that Sir <hi>Thomas Glemham</hi> the late Governour of <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſhould be diſcharged of his impriſoment; but no reparation made him. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he releaſed upon this Order.</p>
                  <p>About this time, that grand Incendiary betwixt the two Nations, <hi>Henderſon</hi> (the Scot) died. The King confuted all his Arguments which he urged to perſwade him to take the Covenant and ſigne the Propoſitions; which forced the poore Scot into another World to ſee if he could learne any better.</p>
                  <p>14. The Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> died; ſome ſay of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy, ſome of a Surfer, others ſay of the Plague, and many thinke he was Poyſoned; Whether he was or not, it is moſt certaine that the Parl. ſuſpected him to harbour ſome Honourable thoughts of His Majeſty, and that was enough to kill him, by one meanes, or other. It is confeſſed by all men, that he dyed ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly: And that he was the firſt Generall of the Grand Rebellion: that will not die ſuddainly.</p>
                  <p>16. The Caſtle of S. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Silly</hi> and the Iſland ſurrendred.</p>
                  <p>20. Ordered that His Majeſties Perſon ſhould be diſpoſed of as both Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould thinke fit.</p>
                  <p>25. Ordered that the Eſtates of the Lord <hi>Capell,</hi> Lord <hi>cottington,</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>wincheſter,</hi> E. of <hi>worceſte,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Smith,</hi> and many others ſhould be ſold. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>29. Sir <hi>John Geere</hi> (Alderman) Elected Lord Major by the City of <hi>London.</hi> This Gentleman is daily derided (by the Factious Perſons in and about <hi>London</hi>) with the Title of the Queenes Knight: How well he may deſerve ſo Honourable an Epithite, Time will manifeſt.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:38"/>
                  <p>30. <hi>M. Culham</hi> and <hi>M. Edmonds</hi> (formerly elected Sheriftes for <hi>London</hi>) were ſworn at the <hi>Exchequer</hi> bar, at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="October" type="month">
                  <head>October</head>
                  <p>1. Ordered that 5000 1. ſhould be paid to the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the late Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> for defraying the Charge of his Funerall, &amp;c. 500. 1. and a part of the Communion Booke would have buried him like a Chriſtian; But 10000. 1. would<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not wipe away the ſtaine of his Name and Honour, whoſe memory will live in the Title of the firſt Leader of the—<hi>Anno</hi> 1642.</p>
                  <p>Ord red alſo that 4500. 1. which was due to the Counteſſe of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> ſhould be to the State. Alas (good Lady!) nothing of his, Alive, nor dead.</p>
                  <p>Ordered that an Ordnance ſhould be forthwith pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for Eſtating 5000. 1. <hi>Per annum,</hi> upon Sir <hi>Tho: fairfax.</hi> So he gets more by his Rebellion, then ever his Predeceſſors did for their Loyalty.</p>
                  <p>5. And now that the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> is dead, <hi>M. Peters</hi> gets an Ordnance paſſed for the payment of two hundred pounds <hi>Per annum,</hi> and his heires for ever out of the Eſtates of the Earle of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and other Delinquents excepted againſt in the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p>But let him take heed, the E. of <hi>Clamorgan</hi> be not a greater enemy to him, then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi> was: What a Curſe it is ſor <hi>M. Peters</hi> to be troubled with Earles?</p>
                  <p>6. Ordered, That whereas all Commiſſions to Sea Captaines ranne formerly in the name of the King and Parliament, they ſhould be altered, and made in the name of the Parliament only. Any thing (you ſee) rather then f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ile, provided it propagate the Cauſe, but let them remember The veſſells are His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:39"/>
                  <p>12 Commiſſioners from <hi>Ireland</hi> came to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> to treat on the behalfe of the Marqueſle of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>14. The Scots Papers concerning the Diſpoſall of the Kings Perſon ſeized on, and the Scots Warrant for printing of them, <hi>adjudged invallid,</hi> the Printers and Stationers impriſoned.</p>
                  <p>17. Ordered that the Marqueſſe of Hartford, nor any that had ever borne Armes againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould be ſuffered to goe with the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his Corps to ſee his laſt Rights performed. Was not this a horrible diſhonour and griefe (thinke you) to the Cavalier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>?</p>
                  <p>22. The E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his Funerall ſolemnized with more Ceremony, and ſuperſtitious foolery then ever was the Aſhes of S. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> by the monks of that Age.</p>
                  <p>23. Ordered that the Judges of the Serjeants Inns, Benchers of the Innes of Court, and the Principalls of the Inns of Chancery, ſhould take care that none of thoſe Societies that had borne Armes againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſhould be admitted to live in any of the ſaid Societies. Which contradicts all Chriſtian Charity, and violates, the Articles of <hi>Oxford,</hi> as formerly wee not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</p>
                  <p>26. <hi>Denbigh</hi> Caſtle ſurrendred.</p>
                  <p>29. Sir <hi>John Gere,</hi> formerly Elected Lord Major of the City of <hi>London,</hi> was ſworne at <hi>VVeſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>31. The Speakers of the two Houſes, made keepers of the Counterfeit Great Seale, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="November" type="month">
                  <head>November</head>
                  <p>3. The Parl. begun to fit at <hi>Edenborough:</hi> Sure this day is fatall to all Parliaments.</p>
                  <p>17. This day the Ordnance for raiſeing the 200000. l. for the Rebellious Army of the Scots, to
<pb facs="tcp:42953:39"/> betray and deliver His majeſty into the hands of the blood-thirſty Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> was paſſed.</p>
                  <p>26. The E. of <hi>Eſſex</hi> beheaded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="December" type="month">
                  <head>December</head>
                  <p>8. The Treaty with Scottiſh Commiſſioners for the payment of the firſt 200000. l and their martch out of the Kingdome was concluded.</p>
                  <p>12. An Order was made (upon the motion of the Earle of <hi>Pembrooke;</hi>) That all Papiſts and ſuch as had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orne Armes againſt the Parliament, ſhould depart the Lines of Communication, and 20. miles further, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as ſhould get Tickets from the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall, for to ſtay and attend their Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions) and not to returne againe within 2. months. Which very day the ſaid Earle of <hi>Pemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ookes</hi> houſe at <hi>wilton</hi> neere <hi>Salisbury,</hi> was burnt down to the ground, whereby it is ſuppoſed he loſt above 20000. l. A juſt judgement of God on ſo malicious a perſon.</p>
                  <p>16. The money for the treacherous Scots (being 36 cart loads) martched out of London.</p>
                  <p>19. The Citie Petition preſented; and high Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions were pitched upon for obtaining a ſpeedy and poſitive Anſwer from the Parl. but they received onely thanks for their Deſires: and of a ſudden the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Horſe of Sir <hi>The: Fairfax</hi> his Army were drawn neerer London, to keep the citizens in awe.</p>
                  <p>20. His Majeſty diſpatcht his 12. moſt gracious Meſſage to the great men at Weſtminſt. wherein he propoſed and deſired rgaine to come to London, or any of his Houſes thereabouts, upon the publique faith and ſecurity of his two Houſes of Parl. and the Scottiſh Commiſſioners, that he might be there with honour, freedome and ſafety, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>28. But inſtead of returning him an Anſwer, the Higher Houſe voted, That there might not be any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſonall Treaty upon the Propoſitions; To
<pb facs="tcp:42953:40"/> which the Commons aſſented, and added a further vote, That the King comming to <hi>Holmby</hi> houſe, &amp; the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Army gone out of this Kingdome, the two Houſes of Parliament will then joyne with our Brethren of Scotland in all poſſible meanes to perſwade the King to paſſe the Propoſitions; and if he refuſe, that then the Houſes will doe nothing that may break the union and affection of the two Kingdomes, but to preſerve the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="January" type="month">
                  <head>January</head>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>9. And now they perceive the game is done, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſhare the ſtakes, for this day it was Ordered that the Lord <hi>Say</hi> ſhould have</cell>
                           <cell>10000. l.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sir <hi>Rowland Wandesford</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>5000. l.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sir <hi>Benjamin Rudyard</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>6000. l.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>3000 l.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell cols="2">Juſt 24000. l. in one day.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. Went thoſe Lords and Commons from Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, who were appointed by the Parl. to receive His Majeſty from the hands of the treacherous Scots, and attend Him to <hi>Holmby.</hi> This night they lay at <hi>Dunſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> a very fit place for them, if you mark it.</p>
                  <p>18, 19. The Houſe of Commons paſſed ſeverall Votes for allowances to be given to ſuch of themſelves as could pretend to have ſuſtained any loſſes or ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in the yeare 3 <hi>Caroli,</hi> and particularly</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>To the Earle of <hi>Northumberland</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>10000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Maſter <hi>Vaſſall</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>10000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Maſter <hi>Selden</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sir <hi>John Eliots</hi> children</cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sir <hi>Will. Strodes</hi> poore kindred</cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Maſter <hi>Benſamin Valentine</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>M. <hi>Peter Hamond's</hi> ſucceſſors</cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>M. <hi>Walter Long</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <pb facs="tcp:42953:40"/>Sir <hi>Miles Hubbard</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>M. <hi>John Hampdens</hi> children</cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Denzill Hollis</hi> Eſq.</cell>
                           <cell>5000</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>In tote</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>65000. l.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides 2000. l. to the Truſtees for the ſale of Biſhops Lands, and many hundreds more to petty Petitioners.</p>
                  <p>65000. and 24000. l. is 89000. l. a ſmall pittance, &amp; not worth the mentioning; yet a leſſe ſumme would have ſtopt a great deale of clamour made at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hall gates by a number of poore women and others who have loſt their husbands and friends in their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and yet are ſuffered to ſtarve in the ſtreets for want of bread, whilſt theſe men ſhare the ſpoile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, yea no leſſe then 89000. l. in three dayes; and yet ſee what care they afterwards took for the good of the Kingdome, in deſiring His majeſties Keepers at Holmby to be ſparing in their expences: who out of their providence for preſerving the wealth of the Kingdome, reduced their <hi>Priſoner</hi> to one meale a day.</p>
                  <p>20. The totall charged upon the Exciſe of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was caſt up, and reported to the Houſe to be but 390000. l. Nevertheleſſe it hath plainly been proved in a printed book, entituled, <hi>Londons Accompt,</hi> that there muſt needs be above 4000000. remaining in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptants hands of the Excize onely of the city of London and its Weekly Bils.—And what proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Excize of the reſt of the Kingdome of England and Dominion of Wales may beare thereunto, let all honeſt men judge.</p>
                  <p>21. Doctor <hi>Hudſon</hi> (onely for conducting His maj. into the Scottiſh Army, after the Parliament had deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Him acceſſe to <hi>London,</hi> or any other of His Houſes, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing formerly apprehended at Yorke, and brought up to
<pb facs="tcp:42953:41"/> London) was committed Cloſe Priſoner to the Tower for Treaſon, and Ordered that none ſhould ſpeak with Him, but in the preſence of His Keeper. Such are the Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orts, and ſuch the Rewards of Obedience and Loyalty.</p>
                  <p>30. The Perfidious Scots ſurrendred up <hi>New caſtle</hi> to the Parliament; Preſented a Declaration to His Majeſty; and the Commiſſioners ſent from <hi>London</hi> received His Majeſty Priſoner, and tooke the Charge of him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="February" type="month">
                  <head>February</head>
                  <p>3. The laſt 100000. l. was paid to the Treacherous Scots: The Houſe of Lords publiſhed a Declaration wherein they ſet forth, that the Compoſitions made at <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> Hall, were not by Ordinance, and ſo the Sequeſtrators in the Countries not bound to obſerve them, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The Houſe (you know who we meane) Ordered, that His Majeſties Plate, which was appropriated to an holy uſe, and ſtood uſually upon the Communion Table, and in the Veſtry at <hi>White-hall</hi> Chappell, ſhould be melted for the ſervice of the State: Now let all Moderate men determine, whether this was done out of contempt to His Majeſtie and the Church, or for meere neceſſity, the Common-Stock being ſo lately drained of 89000. l. But we have heard a ſtory of a Taylor, who had gotten ſuch a habit of theeveing, that rather then he would forget the main Principall of his profeſſion, he would pilfer the very Ruſhes where he came to keep his Lime-twiggs in Action.</p>
                  <p>The ſimilie may hold, ſave only in this; The one ſtitches together, the other rents in peeces.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> ſent a Letter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to Sir <hi>Thomas Wharton,</hi> and Major <hi>Salloway,</hi> with propoſitions therein encloſed, for the ſurrender of <hi>Dublin</hi> to the Parliament.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42953:41"/>
                  <p>7. the Houſe of Lords were this day perſwaded by the Commons, to paſſe a Declaration to recall their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Declaration publiſhed againſt the power of the Committee at <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall,</hi> and to joyne with them in another of their drawing up for the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of that Committee, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>9. Some of the <hi>London</hi> Apprentices Petitioned the Lords for a Play day once a Moneth.</p>
                  <p>10. Ordered that the Library of the late Arch Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>canterbury</hi> ſhould be imployed and diſpoſed for the ſervice of the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>11. The Treacherous Army of the Scots martched over <hi>Tweed,</hi> at <hi>Kelſey</hi> and <hi>Barwick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>12. <hi>Barwick</hi> quitted and the Garriſon diſman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled.</p>
                  <p>15. A great Tumult in Smithfield; The Exciſe houſe pulled downe and burnt, the bookes torne in peeces, and (as the Clerkes ſay) 80. l. in money ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but we heare not of a penny that was found in the aſhes: This was a happy day for the Exciſe men. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Butchers were apprehended about it, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Priſon; but we heard not of any further pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
                  <p>16. His Maj. was led Captive to <hi>Holmby.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>17. His Majeſty ſent a Meſſage to both Houſes, wherein he deſired to be attended by ſome of His Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, not only for the exerciſe of his Conſcience, but alſo for the clearing of His judgement concerning the preſent differences in Religion, and therein named 12. Reverend and Orthodox Divines <hi>viz.</hi> B. <hi>London,</hi> B. <hi>Salisbury,</hi> B. <hi>Peterborough,</hi> D. <hi>Shelden,</hi> Clerk of the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, D. <hi>Marſh.</hi> Deane of York, D. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> D. <hi>Baily,</hi> D. <hi>Heywood,</hi> D. <hi>Beale,</hi> D. <hi>Fuller,</hi> D. <hi>Hammond,</hi> D. <hi>Tailor.</hi> Whereof he deſired that at leaſt two might have free liberty to wait upon him, for the diſcharge of their Duty to His Majeſty, according to their function:
<pb facs="tcp:42953:42"/> Upon reading whereof, they Ordered Wedneſday fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing (being the 24. day) to returne Anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                  <p>18. The Houſe Ordered, That a Body of 5400. Horſe and 1000. Dragoones ſhould be continued, and maintained at the Charge of the Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>22. A Letter was ſent to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> for the Granting of his Propoſitions, The Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland</hi> arrived at <hi>Corke</hi> in <hi>Munſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>27. The French Ambaſſadour had Audience: His deſire was for a happy accommodation betweene the King and Parliament; and preſented himſelfe as a mediator betwixt them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>March</head>
                  <p>1. The Apprentices of <hi>London,</hi> Petition againe for Play daies, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>6. His majeſty after 17. dayes Expectation of an Anſwer to His former meſſage of the 17 of <hi>February,</hi> renewed the ſame, and ſent it to the Houſes at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> wherein amongſt many other ſweet and pious expreſſions, He aſſured them, that He could not as He ought take into conſideration thoſe Alterations in Religion, which had and would be offered unto Him, without ſuch help as He deſired; becauſe He could never judge rightly of, or be altered in any thing of His opinion, ſo long as any ordinary way of finding out the truth was denyed him: but when this was granted him, His Majeſty promiſed them faithfully not to ſtrive for victory in Argument, but to ſeek and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to truth, according to that judgement which God had given Him, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>10. This day was ſet apart for a day of Humiliation <hi>for the growth of Hereſies and Blaſphemies, &amp;c.</hi> One would have thought they had been <hi>grown</hi> to a ſufficient number already: The Humble-men were much afraid
<pb facs="tcp:42953:42"/> of being interrupted in their devotion, by the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, (whom they account the prime Heretiques) and therefore they ſet ſtrong Guards both of Horſe &amp; Foot throughout the City and Suburbs.</p>
                  <p>The ſame day the Catholique Iriſh had a generall Rendezvouz at <hi>Laughlin</hi> bridge, not far from <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>19. Sir <hi>John Clotworthy,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and Major <hi>Saloway,</hi> received Inſtructions to treat with Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> about the 8000. Foot and 2000. Horſe that had been formerly voted to be ſent for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>21. This day being Sunday in the afternoone, there happened a notable Inſurrection amongſt the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices and others in Moorefields, (occaſioned upon the apprending of ſome who were found drinking in an Alehouſe;) who drew into a head, and aſſaulted, broke downe and plundred the Houſe of Juſtice <hi>Hub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> and forced him and his ſervants to ſhift for their lives: Thre were divers hurt by ſmall ſhot from the houſe before entrance, but not any killed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:42953:43"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>THere remaines now (Reader) nothing to compleat this ſhort-ſad ſtory, but a Catalogue of the perſons of note ſlaine within this Kingdome ſince the beginning of theſe bloody warres, (not to ſpeake of thoſe many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of inferiour Ranke) which may well Challenge even from an Adamantine heart, the tribute of a blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Eye, the rather, ſince theres hardly any ſtory can parallel theſe Calamities, which if truly reſented, will exact from all good Chriſtians an earneſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ſupplication, that Almighty God would pleaſe to avert his Judgements from us; to ſet a Period to theſe diſtractions; and to preſerve our moſt Gracious King from the fury of his Enemies; to deliver him out of their bloody hands; and (in his owne due time) to re-eſtabliſh him in his Throne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_dead">
            <pb facs="tcp:42953:43"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of the names of all or the moſt part of the Lords, Knights, Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and perſons of quality ſlaine or executed by Law Martiall on both ſides, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this unnaturall Warre to the 25. of <hi>March.</hi> 1647.</head>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <head>But before we proceed to give you the Names, we muſt in duty breathe forth ſome pious Eju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations in memory of ſo many gallant ſouls, ſlain on His Majeſties part.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>IMmortall Spirits,</hi> whoſe tranſcendent worth</l>
                           <l>Hath made you ſuch, while it hath brought you forth</l>
                           <l>By a moſt glorious Birth, into a Light</l>
                           <l>Holds no alternate courſe with darkſome Night.</l>
                           <l>Refulgent Starres, in Honour's Orbe you ſhine,</l>
                           <l>Of the firſt Magnitude: Who did decline</l>
                           <l>No <hi>Combats,</hi> ſignall <hi>Enterpriſes,</hi> or</l>
                           <l>The wants and ſuff'rings that attend on <hi>War;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>But fought for <hi>Church,</hi> for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and your <hi>Lawes,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>In all things diſadvantag'd, ſave your Cauſe</l>
                           <l>And valiant hearts, which made you bold t'oppoſe</l>
                           <l>Your noble Bloud againſt ignoble Foes.</l>
                           <l>You need no Marble <hi>Statua's,</hi> or <hi>Braſſe</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>To help tranſmit your Actions; which ſhall paſſe</l>
                           <l>To all ſucceeding Ages, by the Tongues</l>
                           <l>Of learned <hi>Bards,</hi> the ſubject of their Songs.</l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:42953:44"/>
                           <l>No Flux of Time ſhall cancell any Name,</l>
                           <l>Your ſwords have graven on the leaves of Fame:</l>
                           <l>Who ſwell'd her breaſt with your departing breath,</l>
                           <l>To trumpet loud the Glories of your Death.</l>
                           <l>Wherein the living wiſh with you a roome,</l>
                           <l>To draw immortall Honours from that <hi>Toombe,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Which ſhaded ſtands with noble <hi>Palmes</hi> that ſpring</l>
                           <l>From the pure bloud you ſhed for <hi>Charles your King;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>On whoſe perpeſſions may the Heav'ns looke downe,</l>
                           <l>In vindication of his injur'd <hi>Crowne.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>EARLES &amp; LORDS</hi> Slain on His Majeſties part.</head>
               <item>EArle of <hi>Linſey,</hi> ſlain at Edgehill battell, <hi>October</hi> 23. 1643.</item>
               <item>Earle of <hi>Northampton,</hi> ſlain at Hopton heath in Staff. ſhire, <hi>March</hi> 19. 1642.</item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Carnarvon,</hi> at Newbery firſt battel, <hi>Sep.</hi> 17. 1643.</item>
               <item>Earle of <hi>Sunderland</hi> there alſo.</item>
               <item>Earle of <hi>Litchfield,</hi> ſlaine at Routon-heath in Cheſhire. <hi>Sept.</hi> 29. 1645.</item>
               <item>Earle of <hi>Kingſton,</hi> near <hi>Gainsborough.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Denaigh</hi> received his deaths wound at Burmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham.</item>
               <item>Marqueſſe <hi>de Vieuville,</hi> a French Lord, ſlaine at New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Lord Viſcount <hi>Fawlkland,</hi> ſlaine there alſo.</item>
               <item>Lord <hi>d'Aubigny,</hi> at Edghill.</item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Iohn Steward,</hi> near Alresford in Hampſhire.</item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Grandiſon,</hi> received his deaths-wound at Briſtow.</item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Cary,</hi> ſlaine at Marſton-Moore, <hi>Iuly</hi> 1644.</item>
               <item>Baron <hi>Dene,</hi> (kinſman to the Prince of Orange) ſlaine at Nottingham.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Edward Sackvile,</hi> (ſonne to the Earl of Dorſet) moſt barbarouſly murthered near <hi>Oxford,</hi> by ſome of <hi>Brownes</hi> ſouldiers from Abbington.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:44"/>
               <head>Baronets &amp; Knights.</head>
               <item>Sir <hi>Edmund Verney,</hi> his Majeſties Standard-bearer, ſlain at Edghill.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Bevill Grenvile,</hi> at Lanſdowne, <hi>July</hi> 5. 1643.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Nicholas Slaynning,</hi> at Briſtow, <hi>July</hi> 26. 1643.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Rich: Lawdy,</hi> at Cover in Gloc:ſhire.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Ingram Hopton,</hi> at Winsby fight near Horn-caſtle, <hi>Octob.</hi> 1643.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>George Bowles,</hi> at Winsby fight near Horn-caſtle, <hi>Octob.</hi> 1643.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>William Butler,</hi> ſlaine at Cropedy Bridge, <hi>Iune</hi> 29. 1644.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>William Clarke,</hi> ſlaine at Cropedy Bridge, <hi>Iune</hi> 29. 1644.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Thom: Metham,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Will: Lambton,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Anth: Maunſell,</hi> at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Smith,</hi> near Alresford in Hampſhire.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Anth: St Litger</hi> at Newbery ſecond Battell, <hi>Octob.</hi> 27. 1644.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Henry Gage,</hi> at Cullom-Bridge near Abbington, <hi>Ian.</hi> 11. 1644.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Michael Earnly,</hi> ſlain at the ſurpriſall of Shrewsb.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Girlington,</hi> near Melton-Mowbray in Leiceſt. ſhire.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>William Manwaring,</hi> ſlain at Cheſter.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Digby,</hi> received his deaths-wound at Langport <hi>in Com.</hi> Sommer.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>William Croſts,</hi> ſlaine at Stokeſey in Shropſh. <hi>Iune</hi> 9. 1645.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Tho: Gardiner,</hi> in Buck:ſhire.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Peter Browne,</hi> wounded at Naisby, dyed at North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampton.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Tho: Dalliſon,</hi> ſlain at Naisby</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Cave,</hi> ſlain at Naisby</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:45"/>
               <item>Sir <hi>Henry Fletcher</hi> ſlaine at <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Bernard Aſtley,</hi> ſonne to the Lord <hi>Astley,</hi> at <hi>Briſtow</hi> laſt ſiege.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Crane,</hi> upon a ſalley there.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Hutton.</hi> at Sherburne in Yorkſhire.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Francis Carnaby.</hi> at Sherburne in Yorkſhire.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerard jun.</hi> near Ludlow.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>William Wentworth</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Charles Slingsby.</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Francis Dacres.</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Goodhill</hi> wounded in Wales, and dyed at Worceſter.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Brian Stapleton,</hi> in Yorkeſhire.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Lodowick Wyer</hi> a Dutch-man, at Banbury.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Phillip Biron,</hi> ſlain at Yorke.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Nicholas Forteſcue,</hi> Knight of Malta, received his deaths-wound in Furnace in Lancaſhire.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Troilus Turbervile,</hi> Captaine-Lieutenant of the Kings Life-guard of Hotſe, ſlaine at His Majeſties going from Newark to Oxford.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:45"/>
               <head>COLONELLS.</head>
               <item>COl. <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> (ſonne to the Lord <hi>William Howard</hi>) ſlaine at Peirsbridge in the County of Yorke.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Cha. Cavendiſh,</hi> (brother to the Earle of Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,) near Gainsborough in Lincolne-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> (ſonne of Sir <hi>Francis Howard</hi>) ſlaine at Atherton-Moore in Yorkeſhire; the gaining of that Battell was principally aſcribed to his valour-<hi>Iune</hi> 30. 1643.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>George Herne</hi> ſlaine there alſo.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Ferdinando Stanhop</hi> (ſonne to the Earle of Cheſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field) ſlaine in Nottingham-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Stanhop</hi> his brother ſlaine in defending his Fathers houſe at Shelford in that County, <hi>October</hi> 27. 1645.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Cuthbert Connyers</hi> of Leighton in Durham, ſlaine at Malpaſſe in Cheſhire, in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1644.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Henry Lundesford.</hi> ſlaine at the taking of Briſtow by his Majeſties Forces, <hi>July</hi> 26. 1643.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Buck.</hi> ſlaine at the taking of Briſtow by his Majeſties Forces, <hi>July</hi> 26. 1643.</item>
               <item>Col. Trevanian. ſlaine at the taking of Briſtow by his Majeſties Forces, <hi>July</hi> 26. 1643.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Thomas Morgan</hi> of Weſton, ſlaine at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Beton</hi> ſlain near Gainsbor, in Lincolne-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Herne,</hi> ſon to Sir <hi>Edw. Herne</hi> ſlain near Gainsbor, in Lincolne-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>John Marrow,</hi> ſlaine in Cheſhire neare Sandyway.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Thomas Dalton</hi> of Thurnham in Lancaſhire, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded at Newbery ſecond Battell, and died at Marlborough.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Bernard,</hi> Governour of Cannon-Froome in Heref<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, ſlaine when the Scots tooke that place in <hi>Iuly</hi> 1645.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:46"/>
               <item>Col. <hi>Francis Hungate</hi> of Saxton in the County of York, ſlaine at Weſtcheſter.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Mynne,</hi> Governour of Heref. ſlain on the edge of Gloc: ſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Will: Baynes,</hi> ſlain at Malpaſſe in Cheſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Billingſley,</hi> at the loſſe of Bridgnorth.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Whitley,</hi> ſlaine at Conway-Caſtle in North-Wales.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Pinchback</hi> of Leic: ſhire, received his deaths-wound at Newbery.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Rich: Green,</hi> ſlain at Beeſton-Caſtle in Cheſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> (ſonne to the late Biſhop of Worceſter D. <hi>Prideaux</hi>) ſlain at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Rich: Mannyng,</hi> near Alresford in Hampſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Kirton,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Will: Eure,</hi> (brother to the late Lord <hi>Eure</hi>) ſlaine at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Iohn Fenwick,</hi> there alſo.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Lime in Dorſet-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>St George,</hi> at the ſtorming of Leic. by His Majeſties Forces.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Dalby,</hi> ſlaine at Winkfield Mannor in Darby-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Bentall,</hi> in Shropſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Phillips,</hi> near Wincheſter.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Taylor,</hi> at the loſſe of Briſtow.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Will: Wynn,</hi> at Wem in Shropſh.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Bawd,</hi> at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Guthbert Clifton,</hi> ſlain near Mancheſter.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Leake</hi> (ſonne to the Lord <hi>Deincourt,</hi> now Earle of ſlain at or near Newark.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Iames Chidley.</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Dartmouth.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Bowles,</hi> ſlain at Alton in Hampſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Hugh Windham,</hi> ſlain in Dorſet-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Rich: Poore,</hi> ſlain in Wales.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Pert</hi> received his deaths-wound in Cornwall, when Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax</hi> was there.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:46"/>
               <head>Lieutenant-Colonels.</head>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Tho: Markham</hi> of Allerton in the County of Notingham, ſlaine with his Coll: <hi>Cavendiſh,</hi> neare Gainsborough.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Monroe,</hi> ſlain at Edghill.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Lancelot Holtby,</hi> ſlain at Branceford.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Colt,</hi> ſlain at Radcoat.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>George Preſton,</hi> ſlain at Bradford in Yorkſhire.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Howard,</hi> at Landſdowne.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Ward,</hi> at Landſdowne.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Wintour,</hi> ſlain in Gloc: ſhire.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Pavier,</hi> ſlain at Lincolne.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Iohnſon,</hi> ſlain upon a ſally at Baſing.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Haggerſton,</hi> of Haggerſton-Caſtle in Northumb. received his deaths-wound at Preſton in Lancaſhire.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Liſle,</hi> ſlain at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Iordan Metham,</hi> ſlain at the relief of Pontefract-Caſtle, <hi>March</hi> 1. 1644.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Iohn Gower,</hi> ſlaine in the ſiege of Scarborough-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Stonywood,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Tho: Eure</hi> (eldeſt ſonne to Sir <hi>Will: Eure</hi>) ſlaine at Newbery.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Lawſon,</hi> ſlain at Naiſeby.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Topham,</hi> at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Will: Hoghton,</hi> ſlain at Newbery ſecond Battell.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Phillip Howard</hi> (nephew to the firſt and Couſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>german to the ſecond Col. <hi>Tho: How:</hi>) ſlain at Cheſter Battell.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Michael Conſtable,</hi> of the Sepulchers neare Hull, ſlaine chere alſo.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:47"/>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Story,</hi> ſlaine in Gloceſter-ſhire.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>sayr</hi> of Worſarn in the County of Yorke, received his deaths-wound at Naiſeby.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Moyle,</hi> ſlaine at the ſtorming of Briſtow by His Majeſties Forces.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Ballard.</hi> ſlaine at the ſiege of Taunton in Somerſet. ſhire.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Muddyford.</hi> ſlaine at the ſiege of Taunton in Somerſet. ſhire.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Iones</hi> ſlaine upon a ſally at the ſiege of Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Slingsby</hi> ſlaine at Newbery.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Bolton</hi> at Namptwich.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Sherhurue,</hi> Eſquire, Comptroller of the Ordnance in the Lord <hi>Hoptons</hi> Army, ſlaine at</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:47"/>
               <head>Serjeant-Majors.</head>
               <item>MAjor <hi>Richard Harborne</hi> wounded at Malpaſſe (where his Col. <hi>Cuthbert Connyers</hi> was ſlaine) and dyed at Kendale.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Beaumont,</hi> drowned at Leeds in Yorkeſhire.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>George Pluckney,</hi> ſlaine near Stamford in Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Kendall,</hi> ſlaine at the ſtorming of Briſtow by His Majeſties Forces.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Smith,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Pate</hi> (brother to Sir <hi>Iohn Pate</hi>) ſlaine at or neare Aſhby-de-la-Zouch.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Sheldon,</hi> at Lanſdowne Battell.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Lower,</hi> at Lanſdowne Battell.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Panton</hi> ſlaine in the Weſt.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Thomas Vavaſor</hi> ſlaine at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Threave,</hi> at Torrington.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Cuſaud,</hi> ſlaine at the taking of Bazing, upon cold bloud.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Dubleday,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Huddleſton,</hi> ſlaine at Yorke.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Gower,</hi> ſlaine at Scarborough.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Trevillian,</hi> ſlaine at Newbery.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Turner,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Price</hi> (who commanded Priors Hill-Fort in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow) ſlaine there, when Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> took that City.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:48"/>
               <item>Major <hi>Garneer,</hi> a Frenchman, ſlaine then and there.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Will: Leake,</hi> ſlain at Newbery ſecond Battell.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Heskith,</hi> at Malpaſſe.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Laurence Clifton,</hi> ſlain when Shelford-houſe was taken.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Pilkington,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Armeſtrong,</hi> ſlain at Oxford.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Duet,</hi> a Frenchman, ſlain before Lechlade.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Pollard,</hi> at Dartmouth.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Clarke,</hi> ſlaine at Yorke.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Metcalf,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Wigmore,</hi> ſlain near Ilmiſter in Sommerſ: ſhire.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Wilſox,</hi> at Naiſeby.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Spotſwood,</hi> a Scot, ſlain at Wem in Shropſhire.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Tho: Whitmore,</hi> ſlain at Muſcam when the Newar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers beat up the Scotch quarters, he commanded the Foot in that ſervice.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Deane,</hi> ſlain at the ſtorming of Briſtow.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Dacres,</hi> ſlain at Weſthoughton in ſhire.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Hugh More,</hi> Deputy Pay-maſter Generall to His Majeſties Army, ſlain at Briſtow by a Granadoe.</item>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Weſton</hi> a Phyſitian, ſlain at</item>
               <item>Doctor <hi>Tho: Westby</hi> a Phyſitian, ſlain at Preſton.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:48"/>
               <head>CAPTAINES.</head>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Marmaduke Conſtable,</hi> Standard-bearer to the Lord Generall <hi>Linſey,</hi> ſlain at Edghill.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Hen. Byron,</hi> &amp; Cap. <hi>Kingſmyll</hi> ſlain there alſo.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Will: Laborn,</hi> ſlain at Sheriff-Hutton in the County of York, and with him.—</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Matthew Anderton,</hi> of Cleyton in the County of Lanc.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Plunkett,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Iohn Lampton,</hi> ſlain at Bradford in Yorkſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Joſe: Conſtable,</hi> ſlain at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Will: Bowes,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Will. Williamſon,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Tho: Winkley</hi> (Captain of Horſe under Sir <hi>Thomas Tildeſley</hi>) ſlain in the ſiege of Leverpoole.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Thurſtan Anderton,</hi> wounded at Newbery, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Oxford.</item>
               <item>Cap <hi>Iames,</hi> at Lanſdowne.</item>
               <item>Cap <hi>Ratcliff Hoghton,</hi> ſlain at Preſton in Amoundernes.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Corniſham,</hi> at Lanſdowne.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Hugh Henne,</hi> at Faringdon.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Tho: Whittingham</hi> of Claughton <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc. ſlain at Newbery.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Hugh Hoghton,</hi> at Reading.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Vaughan,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Goring</hi> ſlaine at Newbery.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Robert Mollineux</hi> of the Wood <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc. ſlaine at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:49"/>
               <item>Captaine <hi>Charles Oſborne,</hi> ſlaine near Hartland in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire.</item>
               <item>Captaine <hi>Fry,</hi> at Torrington.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Charles Thimelby,</hi> ſlaine at Worceſter.</item>
               <item>Capt. <hi>Cottingham,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Capt. <hi>Gardiner,</hi> (brother to Sir <hi>Tho: Gardiner,</hi>) ſlain at Tame in Oxford-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Capt. <hi>Iohn Bird,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Rich,</hi> ſlaine at the ſtorming of Briſtow by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Forces.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Needham,</hi> ſlaine at the ſurpriſall of Shrewsbury.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Tho. Mennell,</hi> of Kilvington in the County of York, ſlaine at the reliefe of Pontefract-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Fitz-lames,</hi> ſlaine at Bridgwater.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Cha: Stewart,</hi> at in Warwick-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Bunce,</hi> at Bradford.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Chriſt: wray,</hi> at Bradford.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Iohn Clifton</hi> (brother to Major <hi>Laur: Clifton</hi>) ſlaine at Shelford-houſe.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Redman,</hi> ſlaine at Pontefract.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Will: Fenwick,</hi> ſlaine neare Bolton in Yorkeſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Abraham Lance</hi> (of <hi>Abraham in Com.</hi> Lanc.) and</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Robert Lance</hi> his brother, ſlaine in Cheſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Slany,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Cony,</hi> at Whaley in Lancaſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Rich: Wolſole</hi> of Wolfole <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc. ſlaine at Newbery.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Buſhell,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Farrar,</hi> at Namptwich.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Iames Baſſet,</hi> at or near Lanceſton in Cornwall.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Edw: Row,</hi> ſlain at Wakefield in Yorkeſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Anth: Hammerton,</hi> drowned in ſervice neare Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Will: Symcotts,</hi> (Cap. L. of Lord <hi>Piercies</hi> Troop) ſlain at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:49"/>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Gerrard,</hi> at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Tho: Whitley,</hi> at Harden.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Sares,</hi> ſlain neer Uttoxeter in Stafford-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Tho: Singleton</hi> of Stanyng <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc. ſlaine at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Francis Errington</hi> of Denton near New-Caſtle, ſlain at Rotheram in Yorkeſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Nicholas Fitzackerley,</hi> ſlaine at Leverpoole.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Butler</hi> of Kirkland <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc. ſlain at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Maximilian Nelſon</hi> of Fairhurſt <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc. there alſo.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Will: Lambton</hi> received his deaths-wound at Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Topham,</hi> ſlaine at Carliſle.</item>
               <item>Cap. L. <hi>Burbeck,</hi> ſlaine at Carliſle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Baxter,</hi> ſlaine at Baughton near Cheſter.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Henry Alderſey,</hi> ſlaine at Cheſter.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Iohn Adlington,</hi> ſlaine at Cheſter.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Gilbert Markham,</hi> (brother to L. Col. <hi>The: Mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>) ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Daniel Thorold,</hi> ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Greenbury,</hi> ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Iohn Rookesby,</hi> wounded at Sherburne, and died at Pontefract.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Gaſcoigne,</hi> ſlaine near Melton. Mowbray.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Sandford,</hi> at Namptwich in Cheſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Gilbert Aſhton,</hi> ſlaine at Boulton <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Anthony Awd,</hi> ſlaine in a ſalley at the laſt ſiege of Newark.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Tho: Cole,</hi> ſlaine upon the like occaſion at the ſame place.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Huddleſton</hi> (brother to Sir <hi>William Huddleſton</hi> of Millum-Caſtle in Cumberland) ſlaine at Yorke. This Sir <hi>William Huddleſton</hi> raiſed a Regiment of
<pb facs="tcp:42953:50"/> Horſe for the King, and had 7 or 8 brothers Officers in the ſame Regiment, a Loyall Family.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Dudly Smith,</hi> ſlain at Round-way-downe.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Sam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wenman,</hi> ſlain in Devonſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Orm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhaw,</hi> ſlain in going out upon a party at Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Richardſon,</hi> ſlain upon a ſally at Oxford.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Ioſeph Daviſon,</hi> at New Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Francis Clifton,</hi> ſlain at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Standiſh,</hi> ſlain at <hi>Mancheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Roger Hoghton,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Edw: Bradley,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Mennell,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Edw: Wynn,</hi> ſlain at Denbeigh.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Swords,</hi> ſlain at Denbeigh.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Parry,</hi> ſlain at Denbeigh.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Iohn Lance,</hi> ſlain at Iſlip near Oxford.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Anthony Girlington,</hi> (Unckle to Sir <hi>Iohn Girling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>) was the man that did ſo gallantly charge the Scots at Newburne in the firſt Scottiſh expedition, where he was almoſt cut to peeces in the company of the ever to be honoured Sir <hi>Iohn Digby,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Smith,</hi> but <hi>ultra ſpem</hi> recovered, and was finally ſlain near <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:50"/>
               <head>GENTLEMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOLVNTIERS.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHarles Townley</hi> of Townly <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc. Eſquire, ſlain at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Charles Sherburne,</hi> a young Gentleman attending him, ſlain alſo in attempting to gain his Maſters dead corps.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Sands</hi> of the Vine, ſlain at the Battell of Alresford.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edw: Preſton</hi> Eſquire, ſlain at Ormeſchurch <hi>in Com.</hi> Lan.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sidney Godolphin,</hi> Eſquire, ſlain at Chafford in Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Price</hi> of Waſhingley <hi>in Com.</hi> North<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſlaine in cold bloud, when the Eare of Mancheſter took Linc.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Bale,</hi> (ſon to Sir <hi>Iohn Bale</hi>) ſlaine near Thorpawker in Leic: ſhire.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ralph Langton</hi> of Low <hi>in Com.</hi> Lanc. Eſquire, ſlaine at Preſton.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Iohn Conſtable,</hi> ſlain in Yorkſhire.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Steven Tempeſt,</hi> ſlain at the Devizes.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Cuthbert Ratcliff,</hi> ſlaine when the Scots tooke New-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>The: Latham</hi> of Mosborough in Lancaſh. ſlaine when Pr. <hi>Rupert</hi> came laſt to Newark.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Rich: Latham</hi> his brother in the laſt ſiege of Litch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild-Cloſe.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:51"/>
               <item>M. <hi>Cary,</hi> ſlaine at Shelford-houſe.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Iennyngs,</hi> ſlaine at Shelford-houſe.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Bourſcale,</hi> ſlain at Newbery laſt Battell.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Courteney,</hi> ſlaine in Lancaſhire.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Lames Anderton,</hi> ſlaine in Wales.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Tho: Roper</hi> (ſecond ſon to <hi>Tho: Roper</hi> Eſquire) ſlain in the laſt ſiege of Gotheridge-Caſtle, <hi>in Com.</hi> Hereford.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Steven Pudſey,</hi> ſlaine in Holderneſſe.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Francis Pavier,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Rich: Browne,</hi> ſlaine in the Weſt.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Chriſtoph: Anderton,</hi> ſlaine at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Charles Mohun</hi> (brother to my Lord <hi>Mohun</hi>) killed with a great ſhot at the ſiege of Dartmouth.</item>
               <item>Squire <hi>Creſſet,</hi> ſlain at the loſſe of Bridgnorth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alexander Daviſon,</hi> Alderman, ſlaine at New-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Tho: Ogle,</hi> ſlaine there alſo.</item>
               <item>Mounſiour S. <hi>Paul,</hi> a French-man, ſlaine at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Mort,</hi> Mayor of the Towne of Preſton in Lancaſhire, ſlaine there.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Boniface Kemp,</hi> ſlain by the Parl. ſouldiers, as they were marching (upon the delivery of York) to Skipton.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Ildeſons Hesket,</hi> ſlain by the Parl. ſouldiers, as they were marching (upon the delivery of York) to Skipton.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Here muſt not be omitted that memorable Gentleman Voluntier, M. <hi>Gawen Rotherford,</hi> who though he was not ſlaine in the ſervice, yet deſerves to be had in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall remembrance for his Loyalty, for having had 29 children by one Wife, he trooped under his 27th childe, who was a Commander for His Majeſty at Newark.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:51"/>
               <head>That dyed in or by the ſervice on His Majeſties part, (not to ſpeake of thoſe many that dyed in Priſons at <hi>London,</hi> and elſewhere.)</head>
               <item>SIr <hi>Henry Conſtable,</hi> Lord Viſcount Dumbar, dyed in Scarborough-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Will: Pennyman</hi> Governor of Oxford, dyed there.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerrard ſen.</hi> Governor of Worceſter, dyed there.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Will: Savile,</hi> dyed at York.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>John Beaumont</hi> of Gracedieu in the County of Leic. dyed in the ſervice.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>John Ramſey,</hi> dyed at Newark.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> dyed at Borſtall-houſe.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Green,</hi> dyed at Banbury.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Robert Curſon</hi> (eldeſt ſonne to Sir <hi>Iohn Curſon</hi> of Oxfordſhire) dyed at Shrewsbury.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Smith,</hi> dyed at Newark.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Blount,</hi> drowned near Mancheſter.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Ralph Fitzharbert,</hi> dyed at Aſhby-de-la-zouch.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Rich: Blount,</hi> dyed in the ſervice.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Rawleigh</hi> Deane of <hi>Wells,</hi> who being firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted priſoner to Banwel-houſe, a priſon in the County of Sommerſet, by the Committee of that County, was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards moſt inhumanely butchered by the Marſhall attending the ſaid Committee, who run a knife into his belly, whereof he ſoone after dyed, yet the Marſhall kept his place, and went unpuniſhed: And afterwards the Committee turned the Doctors wife and children out of doores, and his ſonne was forced to fly the Countrey, for that he would have proſecuted the Law againſt the murtherer of his Father.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:52"/>
               <head>Executed by Law-Martiall, or ſlaine by accidents.</head>
               <item>COl. <hi>Blague,</hi> executed for Treachery, the firſt at Oxford, the other at Exeter.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Sadler,</hi> executed for Treachery, the firſt at Oxford, the other at Exeter.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Windebank,</hi> executed for cowardiſe at Oxford.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Cademan,</hi> beheaded at Briſtoll for killing an Officer of that Garriſon.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Scudamore,</hi> ſlain at Briſtoll in a duell.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Charles Blount,</hi> Scout-Maſter-Generall, ſlain at Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford by one <hi>Langſton</hi> an Officer under him.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iames Einyon,</hi> ſlain by the hand of Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſpe</hi> in a duell.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Hornivall</hi> of Worceſhire, ſhot dead by accident in his Chamber at Worceſter, by one in a like Chamber on the other ſide the ſtreet,</item>
            </list>
            <p>We cannot better conclude this ſad ſtory, then in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording the Reader a deſerved Elegy on that gallant Gentleman before named, Captaine <hi>William Lahorne,</hi> ſlaine at Sherriſhutton, who (being firſt asked by the Enemy for whom he was?) anſwered, for <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>holy Church,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> and ſo was inſtantly ſhot dead.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:52"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="elegy">
                        <head>An Elegy upon the much lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted death of Captaine <hi>William Laborne,</hi> ſlain at <hi>Sheriffe-Hutton</hi> in Yorkſhire.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>FOr <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>holy Church,</hi> and <hi>King</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>He dy'd, whoſe <hi>Dirge</hi> my <hi>Muſe</hi> doth ſing:</l>
                           <l>For <hi>God,</hi> in duty; <hi>Church,</hi> in zeale:</l>
                           <l>For th' <hi>King,</hi> in love to th' <hi>Common-weale.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>For <hi>God</hi> he dy'd, with <hi>God</hi> he lives;</l>
                           <l>For th' <hi>Church</hi> he dy'd, which triumph gives;</l>
                           <l>For th' <hi>King</hi> he dy'd, with th' <hi>King</hi> of <hi>kings</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>His bleſſed ſoule <hi>Alleluja</hi> ſings.</l>
                           <l>Thus <hi>God, Church, King,</hi> have each a ſhare</l>
                           <l>In <hi>Labornes</hi> death, a mirror rare,</l>
                           <l>Wherein brave minds may have a ſight,</l>
                           <l>How for <hi>God, Church,</hi> and <hi>King</hi> to fight.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:53"/>
               <head>Perſons of Note, and Commanders ſlaine on the Parliaments part, where the Reader may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that as His Majeſty had on his ſide ten Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen at leaſt, for every one on their ſide, it muſt by conſequence follow, that His Majeſty muſt loſe many more of note then they. Beſides, their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers being for the moſt part Tradeſ-men, of ſmall quality, and leſſe fortunes, when any of them were ſlaine (as doubtleſſe there are many more then are come to our knowledge) there was little cauſe to bewaile their loſſe, and leſſe to eternize their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories.</head>
               <item>LOrd <hi>St Johns,</hi> ſonne to the Earle of Bulling brook, ſlain at Edghill battell.</item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Brook,</hi> ſlain at Litchfield-Cloſe,</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Charles Eſſex,</hi> ſlain at Edghill.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Will: Fairfax,</hi> ſlaine at Mongomery Battell in North-Wales.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Char: Fairfax,</hi> Major-Generall, ſlaine at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Meldrum,</hi> a Scot, Major-Generall, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in Chiefe at the ſiege of Scarborough-Caſtle, did there receive his deaths-wound by a ſally from the Caſtle, commanded by Major <hi>Tho: Crompton,</hi> who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that ſervice with much gallantry and valour.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Will: Brooke,</hi> dyed in the ſervice.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Will: Springer,</hi> dyed in the ſervice.</item>
               <item>Major-Generall <hi>Crawford,</hi> a Scot, ſlaine at the ſiege of Hereford.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:53"/>
               <head>COLONELLS.</head>
               <item>COl. <hi>Sandys,</hi> ſlain at Wike field in Worc: ſhire, <hi>Sep.</hi> 23. 1642.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Iohn Hampden,</hi> one of the five Members, ſlaine at Chalgrave in Buck: ſhire, <hi>Iune</hi> 18. 1643.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Lutterell,</hi> ſlaine at Milverton <hi>in Com.</hi> Som: <hi>Ian.</hi> 24. 1644.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Tucker,</hi> at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Meldrum,</hi> a Scot, received his deaths-wound at Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resford in Hampſhire, and dyed in London.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Prince,</hi> ſlain at Cheſter battell.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Armyne,</hi> ſlain at the raiſing of the ſiege of Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefract-Caſtle, by Sir <hi>Marm. Langdale.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Mallevory,</hi> ſlain at the raiſing of the ſiege of Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefract-Caſtle, by Sir <hi>Marm. Langdale.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Cockeram,</hi> at the ſiege of Scarborough.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Lloyd,</hi> ſlaine in defence of Taunton.</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Iohn Gunter,</hi> ſlain at</item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Pickering,</hi> dyed in the ſervice.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:54"/>
               <head>Lieutenant-Colonels.</head>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Ramſey,</hi> ſlain at Edghill.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Quarles,</hi> ſlain at Branceford.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Stanley,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Scarborough.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Gurdon,</hi> a Scot, ſlain at the ſiege of Heref.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Harrington,</hi> ſlain at Riby in Linc: ſhire.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ureſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> ſlain at the laſt ſtorming of Briſtow.</item>
               <item>L. Col <hi>Richbell,</hi> ſlain in defence of Taunton.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Durſey,</hi> ſlain at Briſtow.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Ingoldsby,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Pendennis-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Frances</hi> (L. Col. to Gen. <hi>Skippon</hi>) ſlain at Naisby.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Cotſworth,</hi> ſlain at the laſt ſiege of Oxford.</item>
               <item>L. Col. <hi>Viccarman,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Scarborough.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:54"/>
               <head>Serjeant-Majors.</head>
               <item>MAjor <hi>Douglas,</hi> a Scot, ſlain at Wykefield in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Francis Sydenham,</hi> ſlain at or near Weymouth.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Gunter,</hi> ſlain at Chalgrave in Buck: ſhire.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rrey,</hi> ſlain at Newbery ſecond Battell.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Heines,</hi> ſlain near Plymouth.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Abercromy,</hi> a Scot, ſlain near Stratton-Audley in Buck: ſhire.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Bradbury,</hi> ſlain at Cullom bridge near Abing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Dent,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Scarborough-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Stawham,</hi> ſlain at Lanſdowne.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Iackſon,</hi> ſlain at</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Done,</hi> ſlain at Sherb: Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Croſſe,</hi> ſlain at Sherb: Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Roy,</hi> ſlain at Pitmaſter in Summerſet-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Burton,</hi> ſlain at Mountgomery.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Cromwell,</hi> ſlain at Briſtow.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Fitz-Symons,</hi> ſlain at</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Bethell</hi> received his deaths-wound at Briſtow.</item>
               <item>Major <hi>Cooke,</hi> ſlain at</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:55"/>
               <head>CAPTAINES.</head>
               <item>CAp. <hi>Liſter,</hi> ſlain at Tadcaſter in Yorkſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Willet,</hi> ſlain at Newbery ſecond Battell.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Iuxton,</hi> ſlain at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Lidcoat,</hi> ſlain near Abthorp in Northamp. ſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Nutty,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Redding.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Zachary,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Scarbor. he was Vice-Admirall, and commanded 16 Ships at that ſiege.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Horſey,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Sherb: Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. L. <hi>Flemmyng,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Sherb: Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Croſſe,</hi> ſlain at the ſiege of Sherb: Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Guilliams,</hi> ſlain at Briſtow laſt ſiege.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Hill,</hi> ſlain at Briſtow laſt ſiege.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Gayle,</hi> ſlain at Briſtow laſt ſiege.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Ward,</hi> ſlain at Briſtow laſt ſiege.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Herne,</hi> ſlain at Briſtow laſt ſiege.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Parker,</hi> ſlain at Cheſter.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Fownes,</hi> ſlain at Tiverton in Devon-ſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Wilkes,</hi> ſlain at Taunton.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Gollidge,</hi> ſlain at Taunton.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Ienkins,</hi> ſlain at Farrington.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Iohn Heynes,</hi> ſlain at Leigh-hall in Shropſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Bennet,</hi> ſlain at Huntington.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Samon,</hi> ſlain at Heightley in Yorkſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Watſon,</hi> ſlain near Uttoxeter in Darbyſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Bowen,</hi> ſlain near Uttoxeter in Darbyſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Wigfall,</hi> ſlain at Barkley-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Hunt,</hi> ſlain at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Franklin,</hi> ſlain at Exeter.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:55"/>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Oglesby,</hi> ſlain at</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Allen,</hi> ſlain near Burleigh in Rutl: ſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Cawler,</hi> ſlain at Newbery.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Bowen,</hi> ſlain at Carlion in Monm: ſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Wilkes,</hi> ſlaine at Bazing.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>George Maſſey,</hi> ſlain at Newbery firſt Battell.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Lacy,</hi> at Branceford.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Williams,</hi> at Oſweſtre in Shropſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Paltiſon,</hi> ſlain by the Club-men at Hambleton hill <hi>in Com.</hi> Dorſ.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Dove,</hi> ſlain at Sherburne-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Pue,</hi> at Marſton-Moore.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Cooke</hi> Commiſſary-Generall of Horſe-proviſions, ſlain at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Tompkins,</hi> ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Selby,</hi> ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Buſh,</hi> ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Hoskins,</hi> ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Potter,</hi> ſlaine at Naisby.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Tho: Cooper,</hi> ſlaine at Higharchall in Shrop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Taylor,</hi> ſlaine at Higharchall in Shrop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Birket,</hi> ſlaine at the ſiege of Scarborough-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Pearſon,</hi> ſlaine at the ſiege of Scarborough-Caſtle.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Middleton,</hi> ſlaine at Awborne-Chaſe.</item>
               <item>Cap. <hi>Hacket,</hi> ſlain at Awborne-Chaſe.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Sellors,</hi> a Sequeſtrator, ſlain at Wirkſworth in Darby ſhire.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:42953:56"/>
               <head>Executed on the Parliaments ſide by Martiall-Law (not to ſpeake of the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>)</head>
               <item>SIr <hi>Alexander Carew,</hi> at London.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> and his ſonne. at London.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Tompkins,</hi> at London.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Chaloner.</hi> at London.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Bourcher,</hi> at Briſtow.</item>
               <item>M. <hi>Yeomans,</hi> at Briſtow.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Beſides many other of inferiour ranke that were exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in ſeverall Garriſons for deſerting their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, or otherwiſe for ſuppoſed Treachery, or for Spies.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42953:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
